<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>VVaters of Marah, and Meribah: or, the source of bitternes, and strife, sweetned and allayed by way of aduice, refutation, censure, against the pseudo-zelots of our age: by Humphrey Sydenham, master of arts, late fellow of Wadham Colledge in Oxford.</title>
            <author>Sydenham, Humphrey, 1591-1650?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1630</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 97 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A73288</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23574</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S125548</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99898118</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99898118</idno>
            <idno type="VID">135617</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A73288)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 135617)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2086:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>VVaters of Marah, and Meribah: or, the source of bitternes, and strife, sweetned and allayed by way of aduice, refutation, censure, against the pseudo-zelots of our age: by Humphrey Sydenham, master of arts, late fellow of Wadham Colledge in Oxford.</title>
                  <author>Sydenham, Humphrey, 1591-1650?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 44 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by Elizabeth Allde, for Nathaniel Butter,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>an. Dom. 1630.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:135617:1"/>
            <p>VVATERS OF MARAH, AND MERIBAH OR, THE SOVRCE OF BITTERNES, AND STRIFE, SWEETNED AND ALLAYED, By way of Aduice, Refutation, Cenſure, Againſt The <hi>Pſeudo-zelots</hi> of our Age:</p>
            <p>By HVMPHREY SYDENHAM, Maſter of <hi>Arts,</hi> late Fellow of <hi>Wadham</hi> Colledge in OXFORD.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Diſpoſui naſum ſecare faetentem, timeat qui criminoſus eſt; quid ad te, qui te intelligis innocentem? De te dictum puta in quodcunque vitium ſtili mei mucro contorquetur.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>HIERON. ad MARCELLINVM.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>Elizabeth Allde,</hi> for <hi>Nathaniel Butter. An. Dom.</hi> 1630.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:135617:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:135617:2"/>
            <head>TO THE FRIENDS INDEEDE, both of my Name, and Fortunes, Sir <hi>Ralph Sydenham,</hi> and <hi>Edward Sydenham</hi> Eſquire, Seruants to his Sacred Maieſtie.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My dearely honour'd,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hilſt I labour to ioyne you ſo cloſely in my reſpects, let me not ſunder you in <hi>your owne,</hi> like two greatmen, who the neerer they are in <hi>place,</hi> the farther off in <hi>Correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</hi> I preſume 'tis no <hi>Soleciſme</hi> to linke you together in <hi>one Dedication,</hi> whom Nature hath twiſted ſo faſt in <hi>one Blood,</hi> and Education in <hi>one vertue,</hi> and Familia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, (a knot, I hope, indiſſoluble) in <hi>one heart;</hi> It is not my loweſt glory, that I can boldly, and in a breath, ſpeake <hi>Kinſman</hi> and <hi>Friend,</hi> and <hi>Patron,</hi> and theſe <hi>three</hi> in <hi>two,</hi> and theſe <hi>two,</hi> but <hi>one;</hi> A rare har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony,
<pb facs="tcp:135617:3"/>where Affections are ſo ſtrung, that touch them, <hi>how,</hi> and <hi>where,</hi> and <hi>when</hi> you pleaſe, they are ſtill <hi>vniſons.</hi> I haue hitherto found them ſo in all my wayes, both of <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uancement</hi> and <hi>Repute;</hi> and theſe ſet me vp in a double gratulation, and applauſe; in my <hi>Hoſanna's,</hi> for you to my God, and then in my <hi>Reports</hi> to men. This is my <hi>All</hi> of <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitall</hi> yet, and yours (I beleeue) of <hi>expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation,</hi> which lookes no farther then an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuous acknowledgement of your <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours,</hi> ſuch as the procliuity of your owne <hi>worth</hi> hath ſuggeſted, not any induſtrious proſeqution of mine, which could haue beene contented to haue worne an obſcurer Title, but that it muſt now vaunt in a <hi>Rich one,</hi> That of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Seruant Kinſman,</hi> HVM: SYDENHAM.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:135617:3"/>
            <head>VVATERS OF MARAH, AND MERIBAH.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>TEXT,</hi> Rom. <hi>12.1.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>I Beſeech you, Brethren, by the mercies of God, to offer vp your Bodies a liuing Sacrifice, holy, acceptable to God which is your reaſonable ſeruice,</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He <hi>Text</hi> hath a double fore-head, <hi>one</hi> lookes towards the <hi>Letter,</hi> the <hi>other,</hi> the <hi>Allegory;</hi> that of the <hi>Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> glances on the <hi>Legall Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice,</hi> by the <hi>Iewe;</hi> that of the <hi>Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory,</hi> on the <hi>Spirituall,</hi> by the <hi>Chriſtian;</hi> the one was a carnall oblation of the <hi>Body</hi> onely, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a <hi>Miſticall,</hi> of the <hi>Affections;</hi> That ſpake in the rough <hi>Dialect</hi> of the <hi>Law; Horror, Blood,</hi> and <hi>Death;</hi> This, in the ſweet language of the <hi>Goſpell, Brethren, and Beſeeching,</hi> and <hi>Mercies</hi> of <hi>God.</hi> Here then is no <hi>Hecatombe</hi> or ſlaughter of the <hi>Beaſt, no Bullocke or Ram, or Goate</hi> ſlaine for immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, as of old; but the <hi>Sacrifice</hi> required here,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:135617:4"/>muſt be <hi>Liuing;</hi> 'tis a <hi>Body</hi> muſt be offer'd, and not a <hi>Carcaſſe:</hi> here's no <hi>death</hi> but of in bred cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions; no <hi>ſlaughter,</hi> but of carnall <hi>luſts,</hi> and <hi>concupiſcences. Affections</hi> muſt be mortified, and not the <hi>Body;</hi> that ſubdued onely, and chaſtis'd, not flaine; and yet ſtill a <hi>Sacrifice,</hi> a <hi>Liuing Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice,</hi> a Sacrifice ſo liuing, that 'tis both <hi>Holy</hi> and <hi>Acceptable to God,</hi> and ſo acceptable to him that he accounts it not onely a <hi>Sacrifice,</hi> but <hi>a Reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Seruice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The words then, as they lye in their maſſe and bulke, are a Patheticall perſwaſion &amp; incitement to the mortification of the old man; preſt on by an <hi>Apoſtolicall</hi> power &amp; Iuriſdiction &amp; that of the great <hi>Doctor</hi> of the <hi>Gentiles, Paul;</hi> Where you may obſerue, firſt, his manner of perſwading, <hi>I Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech;</hi> Secondly, the <hi>Parties</hi> to be perſwaded, <hi>Iewe</hi> and <hi>Gentile,</hi> vnder an affectionate, and charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble compellation, <hi>Brethren;</hi> Thirdly, the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or motiue, by which he doth perſwade, <hi>By the Mercies of God;</hi> Fourthly, the Subſtance or Matter of that which he labours to perſwade, <hi>To offer vp your Bodies a Sacrifice to God;</hi> Fifthly, the <hi>Modus</hi> or manner of it; that's various, expreſt by a threefold <hi>Epithete; Liuing, Holy, Accepble,</hi> Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the <hi>Antitheſis,</hi> in the words following, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Reaſonable Seruice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe are the Parts offer'd to my difcourſe, which vpon the firſt peruſall and Suruey, I thought particularly to haue inſiſted on; But finding that I had graſp'd more <hi>Materials,</hi> then I could ſow and ſcatter in the Circuit of an houre,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:135617:4"/>I was inforc'd to bound my Meditations for the preſent with the two former, leauing the remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, till a ſecond opportunity ſhould inuite me hither; And at this time onely, <hi>I beſeech you Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in the <hi>Originall,</hi> not <hi>Obſecro,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pars prima.</note> as the vulgar reades, but, <hi>Exhortor: Beſeeching</hi> is too Calme and Gentle, and therefore rather, <hi>I Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Obſecro nonſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis aptè. Annot. <hi>Beza</hi> in cap. <hi>12. Rom.</hi> v. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> ſaith <hi>Beza:</hi> But <hi>Exhortor</hi> vs'd onely in this place, elſewhere, <hi>Precamur,</hi> &amp; that from the ſame <hi>Idiom,</hi> by the ſame <hi>Tranſlator.</hi> And indeed, <hi>Faire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> and <hi>Plauſibly</hi> to <hi>exhort,</hi> is in a manner to <hi>beſeech:</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Hortamur e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam ſponte fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cientes, quod de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet. <hi>Bez.</hi> ibid.</note> For not onely the Refractary, but the facile, &amp; ſpontaneous, the <hi>voluntier</hi> in goodneſſe, we <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort,</hi> and <hi>Beſeech</hi> in the ſame Word. And if Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude or Number, doe not too much alter the nature and ſignification of things or <hi>Language,</hi> we ſhall make <hi>Beza's Exhortor,</hi> and <hi>Ierome's Obſecro,</hi> all one by the ſame <hi>Pen,</hi> and <hi>Dialect;</hi> For in this place to the <hi>Romanes,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in the Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular, (which is render'd by <hi>Exhortor</hi>) to the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in the Plurall, is tranſlated, <hi>Precamur,</hi> by the ſame <hi>Beza,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>we beſeech you, brethren,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vide <hi>Bez.</hi> ibid. ot in cap. <hi>12. Rom. v. 2.</hi>
               </note> 5.14. So that 'tis probable, the <hi>Greecke</hi> word fignifies Both, but, here more openly to <hi>Beſeech,</hi> then to <hi>Exhort,</hi> For <hi>Obſecro</hi> comes neerer to <hi>Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricordia,</hi> in the Text, then <hi>Exhortor</hi> doth, <hi>we Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech</hi> euer by the <hi>mercies</hi> of <hi>God;</hi> but, ſometimes we exhort by his <hi>Iuſtice;</hi> And in this ſence, the <hi>Miracle</hi> of the Greeke <hi>Church,</hi> Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chryſ. Aquin. <hi>Eſtius in cap.</hi> 12. Rom <hi>v.</hi> 1.</note> will interpret it, and that for three <hi>Reaſons,</hi> here
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:135617:5"/>
               <hi>Aquinas</hi> tells me; firſt, to ſpecifie and open our <hi>Apoſtles</hi> humility (for ſo the <hi>Wiſe man</hi>) <hi>Cum obſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crationibus loquitur pauper. The Rich man anſwereth roughly,</hi>
               <note place="margin">v. 23.</note> 
               <hi>But, the poore man vſeth intreaties,</hi> Pro 18. Intreaties, not for his owne ſake, but for <hi>Gods,</hi> And therefore <hi>Obſecrare</hi> (ſaith he) is nothing but,<note place="margin">Aquin. <hi>vtſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pra.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ob ſacra conteſtari.</hi> Secondly, that <hi>He</hi> might rather out of loue, moue them by gentleneſſe and requeſt, then, out of feare, command them by his power. And this is not onely his practice, but his precept, <hi>You that are ſpirituall, reſtore him that is fallen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">v. 1.</note> 
               <hi>by the ſpirit of meekeneſſe,</hi> Gal. 6. Thirdly, for the reuerence he owed to the <hi>Romane Iuriſài<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,</hi> the great <hi>Senate</hi> to which he wrote (where there was both grauity and State,) which he la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours to win by perſwaſion, and not by <hi>violence.</hi> And this alſo is not onely his Cuſtome, but his Aduice; <hi>Rebuke not an Elder,</hi> but <hi>Beſeech him as a Father,</hi>
               <note place="margin">v.</note> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5. So that whether in matters na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall, or Ciuill, or Apoſtolicall, the <hi>Obſecro</hi> is both opportune and neceſſarie: But in this laſt more eſpecially: For <hi>I Beſeech you;</hi> is more inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuatiue, then <hi>I Exhort;</hi> and <hi>I Exhort,</hi> then, <hi>I Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand;</hi> And yet (as <hi>Aretius</hi> pathetically) <hi>In Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolo obſecrante,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jn cap.</hi> 12. Rom. v. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Deus eſt mandans, &amp; obſecrans:</hi> In that the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> beſeeches, God both commands and beſeechs too; not immediatly, but by way of a Subſtitute: ſo Saint <hi>Paul</hi> teſtifies of himſelfe, <hi>We are Ambaſſadours for Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.20.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>As though God did beſeech you by vs.</hi> Wee are the <hi>Inſtruments, He,</hi> the mouer; wee but the pipes and Conuoy, <hi>He,</hi> the Source and Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterne:
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:135617:5"/>The waters of <hi>Life</hi> runne from him, by vs; not by him. And therefore the Greeke text hath the particle <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Quaſi,</hi> as it were,<note place="margin">Bez <hi>Annot. in</hi> 12. Rom. v. 1.</note> becauſe God doth not <hi>really</hi> beſeech vs, but <hi>As it were</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech vs in the <hi>Perſon</hi> of his <hi>Embaſſadours,</hi> for ſo it followes, <hi>Wee pray you in Chriſts ſtead,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.20. So that there are <hi>Two</hi> here which <hi>beſeech; God,</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtle. Either</hi> had lawfull authority to <hi>command; He,</hi> as a <hi>Creator</hi> in full right: <hi>This,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aret. vtſupra.</note> as a <hi>Legate</hi> in his name; but they had rather win fairely by a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſionate perſwaſion, then harſhly induce by a rigorous command. And this way of inſtruction beſt ſuites with the ſtayedneſſe &amp; te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>per of Gods Miniſters. <hi>Ne pro imperio dictatoriè prae ipiant, &amp; rigidè poſtulent, quod lenitate, &amp; precibus facilius ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent ab auditoribus.</hi> So <hi>Pareus.</hi> 'Tis true,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>In cap.</hi> 12. Rom. v. 1.</note> that the <hi>Law,</hi> and the Interpreters of it, the <hi>Prophets,</hi> not onely not <hi>Beſeech,</hi> but <hi>Command</hi> and <hi>terrifie;</hi> and 'twas the way then; for ſtiffe-neckes and ſtony hearts, (as the <hi>Iewes</hi> had) requir'd both the <hi>Yoke,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pet. Mart. in <hi>locum.</hi>
               </note> and the <hi>Hammer,</hi> Neither did Chriſt himſelfe (for any light we haue from the <hi>Euangeliſts</hi>) euer vſe this humilitie of <hi>Language.</hi> For <hi>He taught as one that had authority</hi> (ſaies the text) <hi>and not as the Scribes</hi> But after <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the <hi>Apoſtles;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mar. 1.22.</note> and after them the <hi>Fathers</hi> made it their <hi>Rhetoricke,</hi> the chiefe <hi>Engine</hi> of their perſwaſion thorow the generall Current of their <hi>Epiſtles:</hi> And indeed, a true Seruant of the <hi>Lord</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>muſt not ſtriue: Non oportet litigare,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ide</hi> Bez. <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not. in</hi> 2 Tim. 2.24.</note> ſayes the vulgar, <hi>Non pugnare,</hi> Beza, <hi>Muſt be no Wrangler, nor fighter.</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.24. A ſtriker in the Church is dangerous: dangerous? into lerable,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:135617:6"/>no leſſe then <hi>He</hi> that is contentious; For cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely they are <hi>Both</hi> of an <hi>Allyance,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Graee. Interpr.</note> 
               <hi>Qui litigat verbis, pugnat:</hi> there is as well a ſtriking with the Tongue, as with the Hand, and ſometimes a Word is ſmarter then a Blow, eſpecially if it doe proceed from a mouth inur'd to barke, which can nought but raile, when it ſhould beſeech; A Seruant you know, ſhould imitate his <hi>Lord:</hi> Now, the <hi>Lord</hi> is not the God of <hi>Tumult,</hi> but of <hi>Peace,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.33. And therefore, his ſincere and faithfull Seruant Saint <hi>Paul</hi> beautafies with a threefold <hi>Epithete</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">2 Tim. 2.24.</note> 
               <hi>Gentle to all men, apt to teach, patient;</hi> Rare eminencies, &amp; in that <hi>Orbe</hi> they moue, ſpangle, &amp; ſhine gloriouſly; <hi>He</hi> muſt be gentle, not to ſome onely, but to all (ſo ſayes the text) to all, of all ſorts, not the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars of his owne Cut and <hi>Garbe,</hi> but euen to thoſe <hi>Without. Next Teaching</hi> and not barely ſo, but <hi>Apt to Teach,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſtius in cap. <hi>2.</hi> Epiſt. <hi>2.</hi> ad <hi>Tim. v. 24.</hi>
               </note> Apt as well for <hi>Ability,</hi> as <hi>Will;</hi> and to <hi>Teach, not to Compell;</hi> and ſometimes to learne too, as well as to <hi>Teach.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sic etiam <hi>Aug.</hi> lib. <hi>5.</hi> de <hi>Bap.</hi> cont. <hi>Donat.</hi> cap. <hi>29.</hi>
               </note> So Saint <hi>Cyprian</hi> tells <hi>Pompeia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, Oportet Epiſcopum non tantum Docere, ſed &amp; Diſcere, quia ille Melius Docet, qui Diſcendo proficit.</hi> Laſtly, <hi>Patient;</hi> patient two wayes; in reſpect of <hi>Occurrences</hi> and <hi>Men:</hi> of occurrences, firſt; <hi>Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions, Scoffs, Detractions,</hi> are the <hi>Liueries</hi> of the Multitude, which <hi>He</hi> weares with as much humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, as peace;<note place="margin">2 Cor. 4.12.</note> and of <hi>This,</hi> our <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> I know not whether <hi>Complaines,</hi> or <hi>Glories, Maledicimur &amp; Benedicimus, We are reuil'd, and yet we bleſſe,</hi> which ſome Tranſlations reade,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vide</hi> Pet. Mart. <hi>in cap.</hi> Rom. v. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Blaſphemamur &amp; Obſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramus, We are blaſphem'd, and yet beſeech;</hi> So that <hi>Reuiling,</hi> it ſeemes, is a kinde of <hi>Blaſphemie,</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:135617:6"/>and <hi>Beſeeching,</hi> a kind of <hi>bleſsing, He</hi> that reuiles a good man, blaſphemes him, &amp; he that beſeeches an euill, in ſome ſort bleſſes him. <hi>Patient</hi> next, in reſpect of men; not onely of the <hi>Good,</hi> for they ſeldome prouoke diſtaſte, but euen of the wicked and malicious, <hi>Non vt vitia palpet, aut diſsimulet ſed vt eos quamuis à veritate proteruos, &amp; alienos,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſtius in</hi> 2. Tim. 2.24.</note> 
               <hi>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuetudine vincat; Not</hi> that <hi>He</hi> ſhould diſſemble or bolſter vice, but that the <hi>Strag gling</hi> and <hi>Peruerſe</hi> he might reclaime with more facility and meeke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Thus the <hi>Intelligent</hi> man euer applies his <hi>Sayles</hi> vnto the winde, and as that turnes, and blowes, ſo <hi>He</hi> ſteeres. And this was the <hi>Spirituall</hi> policie of <hi>Our</hi> great <hi>Doctor, Factus ſum infirmus infirmis, vt infirmos lucrifacerem,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.22. <hi>To the weake I became weake, that I might gayne the weake;</hi> not weake indeed, (though the two Fathers, <hi>Cyprian,</hi> and <hi>Auguſtine</hi> reade it ſo,) but weake,<note place="margin">Cyp. <hi>in Epiſt. ad</hi> Antoninum. Aug. <hi>Hpiſt.</hi> 9. <hi>ad</hi> Hieronym.</note> that is, <hi>As weake,</hi> the <hi>Originall</hi> vſing the <hi>Aduerbe,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Tanquam, as tho weake.</hi> For weake <hi>really</hi> he was not; So he profeſſes of himſelfe, <hi>Wee that are ſtrong, ought to beare the infirmities of the weake,</hi> Rom. 15.1.<note place="margin">Ambroſ. <hi>in Pſal.</hi> 104.</note> 
               <hi>Strong there;</hi> and yet, <hi>weake</hi> againe, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. with a <hi>Quis infirmatur, &amp; ego non infirmor?</hi> Who is weake, and I am not weake, who is angry, and I burne not; But this <hi>Infirmor</hi> hatha <hi>Tanquam</hi> too,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſtius</hi> in Epiſt. <hi>1.</hi> ad <hi>Co</hi> cap. <hi>9. v. 22.</hi>
               </note> as well as the former, or whether it haue or no, it <hi>Matters</hi> not, ſeeing the ſence is one; For <hi>Hee</hi> ſayes, <hi>He</hi> became weake vnto the <hi>weake;</hi> or elſe, <hi>as it were</hi> weake, that is, <hi>like</hi> vnto the weake; <hi>Like</hi> two wayes; <hi>In minde and worke;</hi> In minde, by an <hi>Affect</hi> of Commiſeration; In worke, by a
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:135617:7"/>
               <hi>Similitude</hi> of <hi>Action;</hi> as a <hi>Nurſe</hi> doth with her Child, or a <hi>Phiſician</hi> with his <hi>Patient;</hi> And in this ſence, his <hi>Omnibus omnia factus ſum,</hi> is to be vnderſtood alſo, I am made all vnto all, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.22. All vnto <hi>All?</hi> how? not that he did <hi>Idot</hi> it with the <hi>Superſtitious,</hi> or <hi>Lewd</hi> it with the <hi>Prophane,</hi> played the <hi>Cretian,</hi> with the <hi>Cretian,</hi> or the <hi>Iewe,</hi> with the <hi>Iewe;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſtius, vtſupra.</note> But, <hi>Hee</hi> was made all vnto <hi>All,</hi> partly by commiſerating them, partly by doing ſomething like <hi>Theirs,</hi> which (notwithſtanding) did not oppoſe the Law of God, or elſe, (as Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> paraphraſes it) <hi>Compaſsione miſericordiae, non ſimilitudine fall aciae,</hi> or elſe, <hi>Non mentientis actu, ſed compatientis affectu,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auguſi. ctiam, lib q. <hi>83.</hi> q.</note> in his ninth <hi>Epiſtle</hi> to <hi>Jerome,</hi> and more voluminouſly, in his booke <hi>contra men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daeium,</hi> 12.<note place="margin">v. 1.</note> chapter.</p>
            <p>Neither was he <hi>all,</hi> to <hi>All,</hi> in way of <hi>Conuerſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> onely, but alſo, in matters of <hi>Diſcipline,</hi> and <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice;</hi> in which he deales with the <hi>Delinquent,</hi> as a diſereet Husbandman with a tender plant, or tree; <hi>He</hi> waters it, and digs about it; and, if then it leafe, and bud onely, and not fructifie, <hi>He</hi> puts his <hi>Axe</hi> vnto it; not to roote and fell it, but to prune it; <hi>He</hi> lops off a ſprig, or a branch, but <hi>He</hi> preſerues the body; Thus, the <hi>Inordinate</hi> muſt bee admoniſhed onely, not threatned; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (ſaith the <hi>Greeke;</hi>) not, <hi>Corripite,</hi> or, <hi>Caſtigate</hi> (as <hi>Caſtellie,</hi> and <hi>Eraſmus</hi> would haue it) but, <hi>Monete,</hi> ſaith <hi>Beza,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eez. Annot. in <hi>2.</hi> Theſ. <hi>5.14.</hi>
               </note> warne them that are vnruly, 1. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.14. So alſo, the <hi>Feeble-minded</hi> muſt bee ſolac'd, and incourag'd, not rebuk'd; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini; Comfort the Feeble-minded,</hi> the ſame chapter
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:135617:7"/>and <hi>verſe.</hi> Laſtly, the <hi>Weake</hi> muſt not be depreſſed but ſupported; <hi>Support thoſe that are weake among you;</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Subleuate;</hi> hold vp,<note place="margin">Suſtinete, infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mu-opitulamini; ſic ex Ambroſ &amp; Tertul. Bez. vt ſupra.</note> as a <hi>Crutch</hi> doth a Body that is lame, or a Beame a houſe that is rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; which word hath reference to that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in the <hi>Acts, Suſcipere Infirmos,</hi> or <hi>Suſtine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re; I haue ſhewed you all things, how that ſo labouring, yee ought to</hi> Support <hi>the weake,</hi> Act. 20.35. Here then are <hi>Weake,</hi> and <hi>Feeble-minded,</hi> and <hi>vnruly;</hi> and theſe muſt be <hi>ſupported,</hi> and <hi>comforted,</hi> and <hi>warnd;</hi> no more; I finde no authority for <hi>Indignation;</hi> I doe, for <hi>patience;</hi> for patience to <hi>all theſe;</hi> nay, to <hi>all men;</hi> in the heele and cloze of the ſame verſe, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Be patient towards all men,</hi> 1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.14. and not onely ſo, but to all men, with all patience too; ſo <hi>Timothy</hi> is aduis'd <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Exhort with all long ſuffering, and Doctrine,</hi> 2. Tim. 4.2. And indeed this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of <hi>Long ſuffering,</hi> is a <hi>Mercifull</hi> Doctrine; we ſeldome finde true <hi>patience</hi> without <hi>Commiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration; Mercy</hi> is the badge and Cognizance of a <hi>Chriſtian;</hi> It markes him from a <hi>Caniball,</hi> or a <hi>Pagan;</hi> And doubtleſſe, Thoſe that haue not this tenderneſſe of Affection, whether in the <hi>Naturall,</hi> or in the <hi>Spirituall</hi> Man, are but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, of <hi>Sauage</hi> and barbarous Condition, <hi>Tygers,</hi> and not <hi>Men;</hi> And therefore as <hi>Mercy</hi> diuides a <hi>Man</hi> from a <hi>Beaſt,</hi> ſo doth it a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> from a meere <hi>Man. He muſt be Mercifull,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mar. 6.</note> 
               <hi>as his Father which is in Heauen is Mercifull. O how beautifull vpon the Mountaines</hi> (ſayes that great <hi>Oracle of God</hi>) <hi>are the feete of him that bringeth glad tydings of good things,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay 52.7.</note> 
               <hi>that preacheth
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:135617:8"/>peace, that publiſheth ſaluation, that ſaith vnto Sion, Thy God raigneth?</hi> Eſay 52.7. Thoſe were ſaid to haue beautiful feete amongſt the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> whoſe <hi>Meſſages were ſhod with loy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſtius in</hi> Rom. cap. 10. verſ. 15.</note> who ſpake comfort to the people, and not <hi>Terror.</hi> Now, what ſuch Ioy and Comfort to the Children of <hi>Sion,</hi> as the glad tydings of good things, thoſe excellent good things, <hi>Preaching</hi> of <hi>Peace,</hi> &amp; <hi>Publiſhing</hi> of <hi>Saluation? How beautifull vpon the Mountains are the feete of him that doth it?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. lib. <hi>32.</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Fauſt. c. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Quam ſpecioſi pedes?</hi> (as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> reades it) how <hi>Precious?</hi> or, <hi>Quàmtempeſtiui &amp; Maturi?</hi> (as <hi>Tertullian</hi>) how <hi>Mature</hi> and timely?<note place="margin">Tertul. lib. <hi>5.</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Marcionem. <hi>cap. 2.</hi> &amp; <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſaies the <hi>Septuagint, Quàm pulchri? quàm decori?</hi> how <hi>Faire,</hi> and <hi>Comely?</hi> which ſome of the <hi>Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents,</hi> (and with them,<note place="margin">Leo Caſtrenſis in <hi>Eſay 52.7.</hi>
               </note> S. <hi>Ierome</hi>) haue read <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (cutting off the three latter vowels) which they expound <hi>ſicut Hora,</hi> that is (as they ſay) <hi>ſicut tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus opportunum,</hi> or, <hi>tempus vernum,</hi> as the <hi>Spring</hi> time, when all things floriſh; ſo that (making the <hi>Text,</hi> mutilated, and imperſect) they would haue the words runne thus:<note place="margin">Schol. Roman. ſequens ſeptua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gint.</note> 
               <hi>Sicut horaa ſuper montes, ſic Pedes Euangelizantis Pacem:</hi> As the Spring vpon the mountaines, ſo are the feete of him that preacheth peace; where all things are <hi>greene,</hi> and <hi>fragrant,</hi> when we are led into freſh, and ſweet, and <hi>pleaſing paſtures,</hi> the paſtures of the <hi>Spirit;</hi> the <hi>Staffe</hi> and <hi>Rod</hi> of the Lord to <hi>comfort</hi> vs, his <hi>Peace,</hi> and his <hi>Saluation,</hi> whereby we may walke cheere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully in the paths of <hi>Righteouſnes,</hi> and ſo follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the great <hi>Shepheard</hi> of our Soules (who will feede vs as his choſen flocke) wee ſhall graze at length vpon the <hi>Mountaines,</hi> the euer-ſpringing
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:135617:8"/>mountaines, the <hi>Mountaines of Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And are the <hi>feete</hi> of him that preacheth peace, that publiſheth ſaluation, ſo <hi>beautifull?</hi> beautifull on the <hi>mountaines</hi> too? what ſhall we thinke then of the feete of thoſe, the <hi>Blacke feete</hi> of thoſe, who, like the <hi>poſſeſs'd man</hi> in the <hi>Goſpell,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Marke 5.2.</note> 
               <hi>ſtill keepe among the Tombes?</hi> tread nothing but <hi>deſtruction,</hi> and the <hi>graue?</hi> and as if they ſtill walk'd in the vale of darkeneſſe, and the ſhadow of death, beate nothing but <hi>Hell</hi> vnto their <hi>Auditors,</hi> which by continuall thundring of Iudgements, ſo ſhake the foundations of a weake-built faith, that they ſometimes deſtroy the <hi>Temple</hi> they ſhould build vp; and in this harſh and auſtere manner of proceeding, they oftentimes exceed their <hi>Commiſsion,</hi> when preſſing too farre the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour of the <hi>Law,</hi> they trench on the liberty of the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> as the <hi>Diſciples</hi> did,<note place="margin">Luke 9.55.</note> who requiring fire from heauen to conſume the <hi>Samaritans,</hi> they text it with the ſeuerity of <hi>Eliah:</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. King. 1.10.</note> 
               <hi>As Eliah did vnto the Moabites.</hi> But the <hi>Lord</hi> of mercy is ſo farre from approuing this <hi>fiery zeale,</hi> that <hi>Hee</hi> not onely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bukes it, but the <hi>ſpirit</hi> that ſuggeſted it. <hi>You know not of what</hi> ſpirit <hi>yee are, for the Sonne of Man is not come to deſtroy mens liues, but to ſaue them,</hi> Luk. 9.56. And doubtleſſe, the deſtroying ſpirit is not the right Spirit: The <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> (you know) appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the forme of a <hi>Doue:</hi> and as the Doue is without gall, ſo ſhould the <hi>Organ</hi> of the <hi>Spirit</hi> be, the <hi>Preacher. Detrabendum eſt aliquid ſeuer itati</hi> (ſaith <hi>Auguſtine</hi> to <hi>Boniface</hi>) <hi>vt maioribus malis ſanandis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. ad Bonifac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de Cor. Donat.</note> 
               <hi>charitas ſincera ſubueniat.</hi> Who would not taxe it
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:135617:9"/>in a <hi>Iudge</hi> as a crime and cuſtome too vniuſt, to be mou'd to choller againſt a Delinquent or Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lefactor, when charity ſhould guide him, and not paſſion? He doubles the offence, that doth both exaggerate, and puniſh it; That <hi>Diuine</hi> labours too prepoſterouſly the reformation of his hearer, that chides bitterly, when he ſhould but admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh, and admoniſh,<note place="margin">Iſid. <hi>lib. 3.</hi> de ſumme bone. <hi>cap. 2.</hi>
               </note> when he ſhould <hi>Beſeech. Qui veracitèr fraternam vule corripere infirmitatem, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemſe praeſtare fraternae ſtudeat vtilitati, vt quem cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ripere cupit, humili corde admoneat,</hi> ſaith <hi>Iſidore, Sweet</hi> and mild perſwaſions, and the admonitions of an humble heart, worke deeper in the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of men, then all the batteries of <hi>virulence,</hi> and <hi>Inuection. Oyle</hi> (you know) will ſinke into a ſolid and ſtiffe matter, when a dry and harder ſubſtance lyes without, and can neither pierce, nor ſoſten it; That which cannot be compa'ſt by the ſmoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inſinuations of <hi>Aduice</hi> and <hi>Reaſon,</hi> ſhall neuer be done by force, or if it bee, 'tis not without a tang of baſeneſſe: There is Some-thing that is ſeruile in <hi>Rigour</hi> and <hi>Conſtraint,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Char.</hi> lib. 3.</note> and takes off from the <hi>Prerogatiue</hi> and freedome of humane will. The <hi>Stoick</hi> tells vs,<note place="margin">Facilius ducitur, quàm trahitur. <hi>Seneca.</hi>
               </note> there is a kinde of generouſneſſe in the minde of man, and is more eaſily led, then drawne; <hi>impulſion</hi> is the childe of <hi>Tyranny,</hi> and holds neither with the lawes of <hi>Nature,</hi> nor of <hi>Grace. Deus non neceſsitat, ſed facilitat.</hi> God doth not <hi>neceſsitate,</hi> or if <hi>neceſsitate,</hi> not compell man to particular actions, but ſupples and faciles him to his Commands. And (doubtleſſe) hee that would captiuate the affections of his hearers, and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:135617:9"/>ſmooth and make paſſable what he labours to perſawde in the hearts of others, muſt ſo modifie and temper his diſcourſe, that it proue not bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or diſtaſtfull; like a skilfull <hi>Apothecary,</hi> who to make his Confections more palateſome, and yet more operatiue, qualifies the malignity of <hi>Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,</hi> by preparing them, makes poyſon not only medicinable, but delightfull, and ſo both cures and pleaſes. <hi>I write not theſe things</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Paul</hi> to his <hi>Corinthians</hi>) <hi>to ſhame you,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 4.14.</note> 
               <hi>but as my be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loned ſonnes, I warne you. He</hi> will not ſhame them, and at rougheſt, <hi>He</hi> will but <hi>warne</hi> them, &amp; that as <hi>Sonnes</hi> too, as <hi>beloued Sonnes;</hi> And if this will not ſuffice, he will <hi>beſeech</hi> them alſo:<note place="margin">1. Cor. 4.16.</note> 
               <hi>I beſeech you bee followers of me, as I am of Chriſt,</hi> in the 16. verſe of the ſame chapter. Calmer admonitions are for the moſt part ſeaſonable, when reproofes ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough and bluſtring, not onely not conforme the hearer, but exaſperate him; and therefore what our <hi>Apoſtle</hi> aduis'd the natural parents, I may without preiudice, the ſpirituall. <hi>Parentes, ne pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocetis ad iracundiam filios veſtros: ne deſpondeant animum:</hi> Parents, prouoke not your children to anger, leſt they be diſcouraged, <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 3. For certainely, <hi>words</hi> are the image of the ſoule, and if they flow from a gentle and meeke minde, they produce the like effects, <hi>Gentlenes,</hi> and <hi>Meekenes;</hi> But from a ſwelling and tempeſtuous ſpirit, they recoyle, as a peece that's ouer charg'd, and ſtart backe as a <hi>broken Bowe;</hi> They prouoke, nay, they diſcourage, and find no better entertainement then the ſtroakes of a hammer vpon an anuile,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:135617:10"/>which the more violently they are laid on, the more violently it rebounds: and therefore Saint <hi>Patol</hi> is ſo farre from obiurgation,<note place="margin">Philem. 7.8.</note> or menacing, that he will not ſo much as <hi>enioyne</hi> his <hi>Philemon,</hi> but labours with an <hi>Obſecro,</hi> when he might haue vs'd a <hi>Mando: Though I might be much bold in Chriſt to</hi> enioyne <hi>thee, yet for loues ſake, Iorather beſeceh thee, Phil.</hi> 7.8. So that where <hi>Loue</hi> is, there is ſtill an <hi>Obſecro,</hi> &amp; where it is not, there is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly a <hi>Damno.</hi> Hence 'tis, that the Pulpit is ſo often the <hi>Mount</hi> of <hi>Terror</hi> and of <hi>Vengeance,</hi> the <hi>Throne</hi> of perſonall eiaculations, the <hi>Altar,</hi> where ſome belch nothing but fire and brimſtone, vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the <hi>Ite maledicti</hi> too vncharitably, and (which is worſt) too particularly; who ſcare and terrifie, when they ſhould entreat, and in ſtead of <hi>Beſeech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> fall to <hi>Reuiling;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 12.11.</note> who vnder a <hi>pretence of feruency of the Spirit,</hi> and ſeruing the Lord ſincerely, ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacke Gods dreadfull <hi>Artillery,</hi> and call out all his Inſtruments of <hi>Iuſtice</hi> to aſſiſt them; his <hi>fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſht ſword, and glittering ſpeare, his bowe of ſteele, and ſharpe-ſet arrowes, his horſe with warre-like trap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pings, neighing for the battell, his ſmoaking iealouſie, and deuouring peſtilence, his flaming metecrs and horrid earth-quakes, his ſtorme, his whirle-wind, and his tempeſt, flouds and billowes, and boylings of the deepe, his cuppe of diſpleaſure, and vials of indignation, his dregs of fury, and beſome of deſtruction, his haile ſtones and his lightnings, his coales of Iuniper, and hot thunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolts.</hi> Thus in fearefull harneſſe hauing muſter'd vp all Gods <hi>Iudgements</hi> in a full volly, they (at once) diſcharge them againſt the pretended
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:135617:10"/>corruptions of particular men, whom their <hi>vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulence</hi> labours rather to traduce, then their <hi>Deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> to reforme; And this is but a ſpirituall di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraction, a deuout <hi>phrenzy,</hi> a holy madneſſe, through which (like the <hi>Lunaticke</hi> in the <hi>Goſpell</hi>) they fall ſometimes into the water,<note place="margin">Marke 9.22.</note> ſometimes into the fire; Nothing will ſatisfie them, but flouds and flames; flouds to o'er-whelme the ſinner, or flames to martyr him; But
<q>
                  <hi>Quis furor, ô ciues; quae tanta dementia?</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Publicke reproofes, when they are cloath'd with <hi>Terror,</hi> not onely diſparage, but dis-hearten; They breake the <hi>bruizedreede,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay 42.3.</note> 
               <hi>and quench the ſmoa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king flaxe,</hi> run many on the ſhelues of deſpaire, where they make an vnhappy ſhipwracke of their faith; and not of their faith onely, but of their body alſo, expoſing it to poyſon, or the knife, to ſtrangling, or to the floud; to the wilfull preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitation of ſome Towre or Cliffe, or the vnnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall butchery of their owne hands; and ſo tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting the body for the ſoule, by a temporall death, at length they feele the torments both of ſoule and body by an eternall death. Thus if <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſions</hi> bee made too deepe in the vlcers of the Soule, and the ſpirituall wound ſearch'd too roughly, it more reliſhes of cruelty, then of <hi>Loue;</hi> and he that doth it, rather preaches his owne ſinne, then endeuours to cure anothers, <hi>Qui delinquente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuperbo vel odioſo animo corrigit, non omendat, ſed percutit:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jſid. <hi>lib. 3.</hi> de ſummo Bone. <hi>cap. 51.</hi>
               </note> Rebukes which taſte of enuie or ſuperciliouſneſſe, do not reforme, but wound, and in ſtead of lenitying and making more tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctable
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:135617:11"/>indifferent diſpoſitions, they ſtubborne them, knowing that reproofes too tartly ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon'd: are the ſeruices of Spleene, and not of Zeale: 'tis call'd <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Zeale,</hi> from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing and boyling of a pot; Now, a pot (you know) not temperatly fir'd, boyles ouer; and certainely if <hi>Moderation</hi> ſometimes blow not the <hi>Cole,</hi> but wee make <hi>virulence</hi> the bellowes of our zeale, it not onely ſeeths and riſes to paſſion and diſtemper, but boyles ouer to <hi>Enuy</hi> and <hi>Vncharita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſſe,</hi> And therefore our <hi>Apoſtle</hi> (deuiding the properties of true Charity from a falſe zeale) makes this one <hi>Symptome</hi> of that great vertue, <hi>Charitas non aemulatur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſlius in <hi>1. Cor. cap. 13.3.</hi> Cyplib. de zelo &amp; Liuore.</note> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.3. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in the <hi>Originall, non zelat:</hi> That is (as <hi>Cyprian</hi> reades) <hi>non inuidet,</hi> enuies not; for zeale in her perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and as it leanes to vertue, is but emula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but ſcrew'd vp to vice, 'tis enuy; <hi>Enuy?</hi> Nay 'tis fury:<note place="margin">Iſid. <hi>lib. 3.</hi> de ſummo Bono. <hi>cap. 91.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Quicquid proteruus vel indignans animus protulerit, obiurgantis furor eſt, non dilectio corrigen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis,</hi> ſaith the Father: what in way of Admoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment paſſion produces, is Reuiling, and not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhment, and doth not touch ſo properly on ſincerity, as malice; And therefore <hi>Enuies</hi> and <hi>Euill ſpeakings,</hi> are link'd with <hi>Guile</hi> and <hi>Hypocriſie.</hi> By Saint <hi>Peter, Lay aſſide all guile, Hypocriſies,</hi> and <hi>Enuies, and euill ſpeakings,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1. A tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate reproofe will mould and worke vs to refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, when an <hi>Inuectiue</hi> fires vs:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>In</hi> cap. 5. Luae.</note> 
               <hi>Ill a pudorem ineutit, Haec indignationem mouet;</hi> faith <hi>Ambroſe:</hi> That touches vs with remorce, and ſlumbers, and becalmes all paſſion; This kindles our In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:135617:11"/>and with that, our ſtubbonrneſſe, For certainely harſh ſpeeches doe not ſo properly <hi>moue,</hi> as <hi>ſtartle</hi> vs, and are like ſharpe ſawces to the ſtomacke, which though they ſometimes ſtirre the appetite, yet they gnaw; And for this Error, ſome haue cenſur'd Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, That if <hi>He</hi> could haue moderated his zeale, and temper'd his reproofes with a little mildneſſe, (eſpecially to the <hi>Empreſſe Eudoxia</hi>) <hi>He</hi> might haue done more ſeruice to his <hi>Church,</hi> and refcued his honour from the ſtaine both of <hi>Impriſonment and Exile.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I preſſe not this ſo farre <hi>(Beloued)</hi> to fat and pamper vice, or rocke and lull men in a careleſſe ſenſuality; Though <hi>I</hi> doe <hi>Beſeech,</hi> yet I would not <hi>fawne:</hi> This were to kill our young with col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling them, and with the Iuie, barren and dead that tree which we embrace. I know, a <hi>Boanerges</hi> is ſometimes as well requir'd, as a <hi>Barnabas,</hi> a ſonne of <hi>Thunder,</hi> as of <hi>Conſolation;</hi> But theſe haue their viciſſitudes, and ſeaſons. There is an <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>circumciſed heart,</hi> and there is a <hi>Broken Spirit:</hi> There is a <hi>deafe Adder</hi> that will not be <hi>charm'd;</hi> and there are <hi>good Sheepe</hi> that will <hi>heare Chriſts</hi> voyce, For theſe, there is the <hi>ſpirit</hi> of <hi>Meekeneſſe;</hi> for the other, <hi>loud</hi> and ſharpe <hi>Reproofes;</hi> If <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bals</hi> heart. be <hi>ſtony,</hi> the <hi>Word</hi> is call'd a <hi>Hammer,</hi> let that batter it. If <hi>Iſrael</hi> haue a heart that is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trite and wounded, <hi>Gilead</hi> hath Balme in it, and there is <hi>oyle of comfort for him that mournes in Sion.</hi> Thus, as our <hi>Inſirmities</hi> are diuers, ſo are the cures of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> ſometimes it <hi>terrifies,</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:135617:12"/>it <hi>Commands,</hi> ſometimes it <hi>Beſeeches;</hi> But let not vs <hi>terrifie</hi> when we ſhould but <hi>Command,</hi> nor <hi>Command</hi> when wee ſhould <hi>Beſeech,</hi> leſt wee make this <hi>Liberty</hi> a <hi>Cloake</hi> for our <hi>Maliciouſneſſe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Pet 2.16.</note> In all exhortations, firſt make vſe of the <hi>ſtill voyce;</hi> and if that preuaile not, <hi>Cry alowd</hi> vnto the <hi>Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet;</hi> and if that be not ſhrill enough, raiſe the <hi>Thunder-clap;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. <hi>l b 2.</hi> de ſermote Domini in monte <hi>ſe m 1.</hi>
               </note> But this <hi>latter, Rarò &amp; magna nece ſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate</hi> (ſaith <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) ſeldome, and vpon great neceſſity; <hi>It à tamèn, vt in ipſis etiam obiurgationibus non nobis, ſed Deo ſeruiatur inteſtinus;</hi> If we muſt needs lighten and thunder, let it bee as from God, not vs, who are to ſcourge the ſinne, not the perſon, except vpon capitall offences, open blaſphemies,<note place="margin">Acts 15.</note> wilfull prophanations. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> then may call <hi>Elymas</hi> the <hi>Sorcerer,</hi> the child of the Deuill, and <hi>Peter</hi> ſay to <hi>Symon Magus, Thou art in the gall of Bitterneſſe, and the very bond of Iniquity.</hi> Rebukes (I confeſſe) too mercifull for the grand <hi>Diſciples</hi> of <hi>Sorcerie,</hi> and <hi>Magicke,</hi> and yet ſowre enough for thoſe other <hi>Nouices</hi> and <hi>Babes</hi> in the ſchoole of Chriſt; Though ſuch alſo are not onely open to the <hi>Checke,</hi> but to the <hi>Rod, Vultis vt in virga veniam?</hi> Shall I come to you with the <hi>Rod,</hi> or in <hi>Loue?</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.21. To wound and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend a little, to profit much, is to loue ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; <hi>Habet &amp; amor plagas ſuas,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ambroſ ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er <hi>1.</hi> cap. ad Cor.</note> 
               <hi>quae dulciores ſunt cùm amarius inferuntur:</hi> Loue it ſelfe hath her whips and thornes, and the more they are layd on, the leſſe they wound, to our <hi>Ruine,</hi> tho not our <hi>Smart.</hi> There is a ſharpneſſe of ſpeech vs'd to <hi>Edification,</hi> not to <hi>Deſtruction,</hi> (ſaith Saith <hi>Paul,</hi>)
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:135617:12"/>2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.10. A religious chaſtiſement, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times more profits, then a partiall conniuence or remiſſion; This may perchance ſoften and melt a peruerſe nature, The other skums it; There is as well a <hi>Cruell mercy</hi> in remitting offences which ſhould be puniſhed, as a mercileſſe Cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in ouer-puniſhing others which might haue beene remitted; And therefore 'tis an <hi>Euangelic all</hi> Commandement, <hi>Sipeccauer it in te frater tuus, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ripe eum, If thy brother ſinne againſt thee, reproue him;</hi> Reproue him? how? openly? No, <hi>Secretò corripe</hi> (ſaith <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) Reproue ſecretly.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aug</hi> de Verbis Domini ſuper illa verba, Sipeta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueriit te frater ſuus.</note> For if thou art knowing his offence, and by way of a taunt or exprobratio doſt diuulge and blazon it, <hi>Non es Corector, ſed proditor,</hi> (ſayes the Father) <hi>Thou art not a Corrector, but a Betrayer;</hi> or as <hi>Origen</hi> aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uates it, <hi>Non reprehendentis hoc, ſed infamantis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Orig. in Leuit. <hi>cap. 23.</hi>
               </note> This is no part of <hi>Reprooſe,</hi> but of <hi>Defamation.</hi> A wholeſome holy Reprehenſion may be viciouſly applyed, eſpecially not ballac'd by thoſe two great weights, <hi>Charity,</hi> and <hi>Iudgement: Iudgement</hi> to mould it, and <hi>Charity</hi> to ſweeten it, otherwiſe we may <hi>Wound</hi> perchance, when we deſire to <hi>Heale,</hi> and in ſtead of reprouing others, condemne our ſelues; And therefore that of Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> is very <hi>Energeticall, Cogitemus cum aliquom reprehendere nos neceſsitas coegerit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. lib. de fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon. Domini in monte. <hi>ſer. 1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>vtrum tale ſit vitium quod nunquàm habui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, &amp; tuunc cogitemus nos hon. ines eſſe, &amp; habere potuiſſe; vel quòd tale habuimus, &amp; iam non habe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, &amp; nunc tangat memoriam communis fragili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis, vt ill am correctionem, non odium, ſed miſericor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:135617:13"/>praecedat</hi> When neceſſity impels vs to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend another (as the Father will haue no repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion without neceſſity,) let vs conſider, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be ſuch a <hi>vice</hi> as we neuer had, and then, weigh that we are but men, and might haue had it; or whether ſuch a one as once we had, and now haue not, and then let it whiſper to vs the common frailty of mankind, that ſo <hi>Mercy</hi> and not <hi>Hatred</hi> may be the <hi>Pule</hi> and platforme of our <hi>Reproofe.</hi> 'Tis true, the words of the <hi>Wiſeman</hi> are compar'd to <hi>Goads</hi> and <hi>Nailes;</hi> and the Reaſon, or Morall rather,<note place="margin">Greg. Hom <hi>6.</hi> ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Euang. in illa zerbae.</note> 
               <hi>Gregory</hi> affords, <hi>Culpas delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentium neſciunt calcare, ſed pungere:</hi> Lapſes and deprauations, they will pricke, and not ſmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. But take heed how they pricke too farre, left bleeding them, they rankle. Applications come too late, when the part begins to gangrene; And therefore ſometimes our <hi>Balſames</hi> are opportune, ſometimes our <hi>Corraſiues;</hi> How to <hi>time,</hi> and qualifie them, the <hi>Diuine Moraliſt</hi> will preſcribe you,<note place="margin">Greg. Moral. <hi>lib. 29.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Regat Diſciplinae vigor manſuetudinem, &amp; man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuetudo ornet vigorem, &amp; ſic alterum commendetur, ex altero, vt nec vigor ſit rigidus, nec manſuetudo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoluta:</hi> Diſcretion muſt be the <hi>Guide</hi> to decline hatred, and auoyde negligence, to blunt and meeken <hi>Rigour,</hi> and to edge and embolden <hi>Soft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe;</hi> that ſo we may not onely rebuke <hi>Delinquents,</hi> as <hi>men</hi> meerely, but ſometimes encourage them as <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and not alwayes terrifie them, as <hi>Aliens</hi> and enemies to the <hi>Church,</hi> but, now and then <hi>Beſeech</hi> them as our <hi>Brethren;</hi> ſo the Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of our <hi>Apoſtle</hi> runs in the words following, <hi>I beſeech you Brethren.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:135617:13"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Brethren?</hi> how? by Nature? or <hi>Country?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pars 2.</note> or <hi>Allyance?</hi> Neither; For the <hi>Romane Church</hi> was then a mixt <hi>Church,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aquin. parte <hi>3.</hi> q. <hi>28.</hi> Art. <hi>3.</hi> ad <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> a <hi>Throng</hi> of <hi>Iewes</hi> and <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles</hi> promiſcuouſly; And theſe could not be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly his Brethren, either in reſpect of <hi>Parents,</hi> or Nation, or Conſanguinity; and therefore, <hi>Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,</hi> by Affection, <hi>Singulari affectu,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aretius in <hi>cap: 12. Rom.</hi> Pareus Ibid.</note> (ſaith <hi>Are<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius,</hi>) And ſo <hi>Pareus</hi> too, <hi>Fratres compellat, vt de amore eius frater no non dubitet, He</hi> vſes this ſweet Compellation, <hi>Brethren,</hi> not (perchance) that they were ſo, either by <hi>Grace,</hi> or <hi>Nature;</hi> but, <hi>Brethren,</hi> that they might not diſtruſt his brother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affection; For though of <hi>old</hi> the word <hi>Fratres</hi> was a common Attribute and name to all <hi>Belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers;</hi> yet, not vſed to the <hi>Romanes</hi> (here) becauſe, <hi>Beleeuers, Sed vt fraternam beneuolentiam,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Carthuſ. in</hi> cap 12. Rom. v. 1.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem, in illis declaret ſuam,</hi> ſaith <hi>Carthuſian; Not</hi> ſo much to manifeſt their <hi>faith,</hi> as his <hi>Charity;</hi> For though many of them were <hi>ſtrangers</hi> to him, and ſome his ſworne enemies, yet notwithſtanding their extremity of hatred, hee would not refuſe to call them <hi>Brethren,</hi> that would be his <hi>Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioners;</hi> Nay, ſuch were his ouer-flowings of <hi>Zeale</hi> and <hi>Loue; Loue</hi> towards them, for Gods ſake; and <hi>Zeale</hi> towards God, for theirs, that he will not onely expoſe his <hi>Body</hi> to tortures for them, but (if it were poſſible) his very <hi>Soule;</hi> And left this ſhould be thought a <hi>Floriſh</hi> meere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>He</hi> calls his owne <hi>Conſcience</hi> to witneſſe it, <hi>My</hi> Conſcience <hi>bearing me record, that I could wiſh,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 9.8.</note> 
               <hi>that my ſelfe were accurſed from Chriſt, for my</hi> Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:135617:14"/>
               <hi>my kinſmen according to the fleſh,</hi> Rom 9.3.</p>
            <p>Thus, the great <hi>Lamps</hi> and <hi>Beacons</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> as they haue abounded euer in <hi>Grace,</hi> ſo in <hi>Loue</hi> too; their <hi>Charity</hi> went hand in hand with their <hi>Zeale,</hi> and ſometimes out-ſtept it; and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed <hi>Charity</hi> is the very <hi>Salt</hi> of <hi>Religion,</hi> the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner of all our <hi>Spirituall</hi> and <hi>Morall Actions;</hi> without which, euen our Deuotions are vnſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoury, our Oriſons diſtaſtfull; and therefore to this great vertue, ſome haue made three Stories or Aſcents;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Polan. Syrtag.</hi> lib. 9. cap. 10.</note> 
               <hi>Dilection, Loue, Charity;</hi> Dilection at the foote; Loue in the mid-way; Charity at top; That, the ground-worke or foundation; Th'o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the walls and body, This, the roofe and bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlement; <hi>Dilection</hi> (ſay they) includes the Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Chooſer, and a ſeparation of the thing choſen from others which are not; <hi>Loue</hi> followes <hi>Dilection,</hi> by which we are vnited in affection to the thing we choſe, and ſo loue; But <hi>Charity</hi> is greater then both, by which we ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the thing <hi>lou'd,</hi> that we endeuour alwayes to preſerue it in our loue <hi>Dilection</hi> is an <hi>Effeminate, light</hi> and tranſitory affection; <hi>Loue</hi> more <hi>Maſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>line,</hi> though ſomewhat violent, and ſo vnſtable too; <hi>Charity,</hi> ſober, and hung with grauity, and inuolues both ſtrictneſſe of <hi>Tye</hi> and inuiolable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Thus the <hi>Moraliſt</hi> will Cryticke on the words; the <hi>Diuine</hi> is not ſo curious, But if he find any difference. <hi>He</hi> makes <hi>Loue</hi> and <hi>Charity</hi> towards God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Polan. Syntag.</hi> lib. 9. cap. 10.</note> the cauſes of <hi>Dilection,</hi> and <hi>This</hi> the effect of the other <hi>Two,</hi> ſo <hi>Polanus.</hi> But indeed <hi>Charity</hi> includes all, hath a diuerſe Aſpect, and caſts
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:135617:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>euery way, like a well-arted eye in a curious Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, ſtand what ſide of it you pleaſe, It ſeemes ſtill to glance and dart vpon you; Sometimes It lookes <hi>ad nos,</hi> to vs, and that is our home-<hi>Charity,</hi> Charity to our ſelues; Sometimes <hi>ſupra nos,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue vs, and that's towards God; Sometimes <hi>praeter nos,</hi> beſide vs, and that's towards our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; Sometimes <hi>iuxta nos,</hi> with vs, and that's towards our neighbour; Sometimes <hi>extra nos,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. <hi>lib. 1.</hi> de Doct. Chriſtiana. <hi>cap. 23.</hi>
               </note> without vs, &amp; that's towards the <hi>Infidell;</hi> Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times <hi>infra nos,</hi> below vs, and that's towards the world. What? Charity towards our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, the <hi>vnbeleeuer,</hi> and the world? and none towards the Text here, <hi>Our Brethren?</hi> Yes, Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity towards our <hi>Neighbour</hi> includes that; or if it did not, Charity towards <hi>God</hi> commands it, <hi>Hoc mandatum habemus à Domino,</hi> This <hi>command</hi> we haue from <hi>God,</hi> that hee that loueth God, ſhould loue his brother alſo, 1 <hi>Iohn.</hi> 4.21. So that this <hi>Diligere Deum,</hi> preſuppoſes <hi>diligere fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trem;</hi> and this <hi>diligere fratrem, diligere proximum;</hi> and this <hi>diligere proximum, diligere omnem hominem:</hi> ſo Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> vpon our Sauiours <hi>Diliges pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ximum tuum,</hi> thou ſhalt loue thy neighbour, <hi>Manifeſtum eſt omnem hominem proximum eſſe depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tandum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. vt ſupra.</note> 1. Booke <hi>de doct. Chriſt.</hi> 30. <hi>cap.</hi> So that, to loue God, doth inſinuate to loue euery man by the rules of Charity; not euery man for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe only, but for God, &amp; therefore for himſelfe, becauſe for God; according to that of the ſame Saint <hi>Auguſtine, Charitas eſt motus animi ad fruen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum Deo, propter ipſum, &amp; ſe; atque proximo,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. <hi>lib. 3.</hi> de Doct. Chriſtiana. <hi>cap. 10.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>propter
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:135617:15"/>Deum Charity</hi> is a motion of the mind, by which we enioy God for himſelfe, and our ſelues, and our Neighbour for our God. <hi>Thou ſhalt loue thy God</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>with all thy heart, and thy neighbour as thy ſelfe.</hi> As thy ſelfe? how is that? with all thy heart too: ſo that <hi>He</hi> ſhares in thy whole man, as well as God; but not ſo <hi>Extenſiuely;</hi> God principal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, thy Neighbour in <hi>Subordination</hi> to him. And queſtionleſſe, <hi>Ratio diligendi proximum, Deus eſt; hoc enim in proximo debemus diligere, vt in Deo ſit:</hi> God is the Reaſon why we loue our Neighbour; for in this reſpect we ought to loue our Neighbour, that hee be in God; and therefore 'tis manifeſt that the ſame <hi>Act</hi> in <hi>Specie</hi> (ſaith <hi>Thomas</hi>) is, by which we loue God,<note place="margin">Aquin. ſecunda ſecundae. q. <hi>25.</hi> Art. <hi>1.</hi> Const.</note> and by which we loue our Neighbour, and ſo the very Habit of <hi>Charity</hi> muſt not onely extend it ſelfe to the loue of God, but to the loue of our Neighbour alſo.</p>
            <p>Neither is this great <hi>vertue</hi> terminated here, but extendeth alſo to our very enemies; and that not onely out of command, becauſe God en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioynes it, but out of Neceſſity, becauſe Charity will inforce it. The very <hi>Lawes</hi> of Charity will haue vs loue our <hi>Enemies,</hi> but not meerely, as our <hi>Enemies;</hi> for that were to loue anothers ſin; but, in <hi>vniuerſali,</hi> as men, and partakers of our Nature; and, not onely, in this <hi>Generality</hi> of loue neither;<note place="margin">Aquin. ſecunda ſecundae. q. <hi>25.</hi> Art. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> but ſometimes, more perſonally, <hi>In ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulo neceſsitatis, ſecundum praeparationem animi</hi> (as the <hi>Schooles</hi> flouriſh it) <hi>In an Article</hi> of Neceſſity, by ſome mentall preparation; <hi>To wit,</hi> That our minde ſhould euer bee ſo prepar'd, that
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:135617:15"/>if Neceſſity did comply, we could loue our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my in <hi>Singulari</hi> too, more ſpecially, more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly.</p>
            <p>And not onely, <hi>Thus,</hi> to our enemie, but the <hi>Wicked</hi> enemy, <hi>Charity</hi> binds there, too; but there as before, <hi>Non culpâ, quâ peccatores, ſed naturâ, vt diuinae beatitudinis capaces.</hi> For there are two things conſiderable in the wicked man<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Nature,</hi> and <hi>Sin;</hi> According to Nature, which he hath from God, he is capable of <hi>Beatitude,</hi> and ſo, the <hi>Obiect</hi> of our Charity; But according to <hi>Sinne,</hi> by which hee ſtands in <hi>Diameter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Debemus in pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catoribus odire quòd peccatores ſunt, et diligere, quòd homines ſint beatitudini ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paces. <hi>Aquin.</hi> ſecunda ſecundae. q. <hi>25. A. 6.</hi>
               </note> and direct oppoſition to his God, and ſo finds an impediment of this bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, hee is rather the But and Aime of our ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, then <hi>Commiſeration.</hi> And therefore, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the <hi>Prophet</hi> is often violent againſt the wicked man, debarring him (as it were) of all Charity, with his <hi>Conuertentur peccatores in Infernum, The wicked ſhall be turned into Hell, Pſal.</hi> 9.17. 'Tis ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken <hi>per modum praenunciationis, non imprecationis,</hi> by way of Propheſie, not Curſe; and therefore 'tis not <hi>Conuertantur peccatores,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 50.10.</note> 
               <hi>Let the Sinners be turned;</hi> but <hi>Conuertentur,</hi> in the Future, <hi>They ſhall be turned;</hi> or perchance too, <hi>per modu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> optationis;</hi> by way of wiſh; yet ſo, that the deſire of him that wiſhes, be not refer'd to the puniſhment of man, but the <hi>Iuſtice</hi> of him that inflicts it; Becauſe God himſelfe puniſhing, doth not reioyce in the deſtruction of the wicked, but his owne <hi>Iuſtice;</hi> or elſe, that this deſire be refer'd to the remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Sinne, not the very <hi>Act</hi> of puniſhment, that ſo the Tranſgreſſion be deſtroyed, and yet
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:135617:16"/>the <hi>Man</hi> remaine.<note place="margin">Secunda ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dae. q. <hi>25. A. 7.</hi> ad <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> And there is <hi>Charity</hi> in this too, great Charity, that we wiſh the preſeruation of the Sinner, when we deſire the deſtruction of his Sinne; But this is <hi>Charitas ſecundùm naeturam</hi> alſo, which is not onely expos'd to <hi>Man,</hi> and the worſt of men, but to <hi>Creatures</hi> reaſonleſſe, nay, to the very <hi>Deuils</hi> themſelues, whoſe nature we may euen (out of <hi>Charity</hi>) loue, foraſmuch as we would haue thoſe ſpirits to be conſeru'd <hi>in ſuis naturalibus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Secunda ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dae. q. <hi>25. A. 11.</hi> Genel.</note> as they are naturally ſpirits, to the <hi>Glory</hi> of that diuine <hi>Maieſtie</hi> that created them, ſo <hi>Aquinas, ſecunda, ſecundae, quaeſt.</hi> 25. <hi>Art.</hi> 11.</p>
            <p>Thus we haue followed <hi>Charity</hi> in her largeſt progreſſe, through heauen and <hi>Earth,</hi> to the <hi>Horrid</hi> pit; From <hi>God,</hi> by <hi>men,</hi> to <hi>Spirits;</hi> if there be a place or ſubiect elſe where <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide or pitch on, <hi>Charity</hi> will dwell there alſo: <hi>It beareth all things,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 13.7.</note> 
               <hi>beleeueth all things, hopeth all things, endureth all things;</hi> Are there Prophecies? <hi>They ſhall faile.</hi> Are there Tongues? <hi>They ſhall ceaſe.</hi> Is there Knowledge?<note place="margin">1. Cor. 13.8.</note> 
               <hi>That ſhall vaniſh;</hi> but <hi>Charity ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer faile,</hi> neuer in matters of <hi>Nature,</hi> or <hi>Grace,</hi> or <hi>Glory;</hi> of the <hi>Law,</hi> the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> or their <hi>Conſumma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; Charity</hi> fulfils the <hi>Lawe,</hi> comprehends the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> and compleats <hi>Both.</hi> All the <hi>Morall</hi> ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues lye ſhrin'd here;<note place="margin">Secunda ſecundae quaeſt. <hi>65. Art. 3.</hi> Concl. Auguſt. Serm. <hi>46.</hi> de Tempore. <hi>1. Cor 13.23.</hi>
               </note> ſo <hi>Aquinas;</hi> all the <hi>Cardinall,</hi> ſaith <hi>Auguſtine;</hi> all the <hi>Theologicall,</hi> Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> though not <hi>ex confeſſo,</hi> yet by way of Intimation; for <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Hope</hi> are not onely <hi>with it,</hi> but <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> it: <hi>The greateſt of theſe is Charity,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. <hi>vlt.</hi> The <hi>greateſt</hi> of theſe? <hi>All theſe,</hi> they are all in <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,</hi> and <hi>Charity</hi> in God; <hi>In God? God it ſelfe, God
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:135617:16"/>is Loue, and he that dwelleth in Loue, dwelleth in God, and God in him,</hi> 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 4.16.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>'Tis</hi> plaine then, where <hi>Charity</hi> is, there is an habitation for the <hi>Lord;</hi> and where 'tis not, there is a <hi>Thorow-fare</hi> for the Diuell; <hi>Religion</hi> is but rottenneſſe without it, and all this front of holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, but droſſe and <hi>Rubbiſh:</hi> Tell me not of <hi>Faith,</hi> without thy works; nor of <hi>Prayers,</hi> without thine <hi>Almes;</hi> nor of <hi>Piety,</hi> without thy <hi>Compaſsion;</hi> nor of <hi>Zeale,</hi> without thy <hi>Charity;</hi> what is <hi>Deuotion</hi> when 'tis turbulent, or <hi>Conſcience</hi> when 'tis pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſh? or <hi>Preaching,</hi> when 'tis <hi>Schiſmaticall?</hi> I loue not <hi>Diuinity,</hi> when 'tis ſtipendary; nor purity, when 'tis <hi>factious:</hi> nor Reprehenſion, when 'tis <hi>Cruell;</hi> nor <hi>Cenſure,</hi> when 'tis <hi>Deſperate: Orall</hi> ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemency hath more tongue then heart: &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that <hi>Zeale</hi> which is ouer-mouth'd, wee may ſuſpect either for counterfeit, or <hi>Malicious.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Beleeue not euery ſpirit</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Iohn</hi>) <hi>but try the ſpirits, whether they be of God or no,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Iohn 4.</note> 
               <hi>for many falſe Teachers are gone out into the world: Into</hi> the <hi>world,</hi> in all <hi>Ages,</hi> and all <hi>Churches:</hi> Let's particularize in ſome, in that of the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> firſt, when vnder a pretence of ſincerity, and ſuppreſſing <hi>Innouation;</hi> (labouring to eſtabliſh the <hi>Iewiſh</hi> ceremonies more firmely,) there were ſome that ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilly cryed downe the very ſeeds of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> as thoſe falſe <hi>apoſtles</hi> did, which came from <hi>Iudea,</hi> vnto <hi>Antioch,</hi> and taught the <hi>Brethren;</hi> That ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept they were <hi>Circum iſed after the manner of</hi> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,<note place="margin">Acts 15.</note> 
               <hi>they could not bee ſaued;</hi> whom <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bas</hi> firſt; and afterwards <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Iames,</hi> and the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:135617:17"/>reſt at <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> both zealouſly did reſiſt, and in their Synod, or firſt <hi>conuocation,</hi> powerfully ſuppreſſe. But this <hi>Pſeudo-zeale</hi> in the time of the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> did but ſmoake and ſparkle (like fire vnder greene wood,) In that of the Fathers, it brake out into flames, when ſometurbulent and diſcontented ſpirits, burning in hatred to the true <hi>Profeſſors,</hi> or leaning partially to ſome fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction againſt the Church, notwithſtanding out of a meere tickling and itch of glory, offer'd themſelues vnto death, for the confeſſion of the name of Chriſt,<note place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ide Eſtius in <hi>c. 13.</hi> ad <hi>Rom.</hi>
               </note> as <hi>the Montaniſts, Nouatians, Arrians, Donatiſts,</hi> whom the Catholicke Church neuer honor'd with the Title of <hi>Martyrs,</hi> but reprobated and caſt out as the wilfull <hi>Patriarchs</hi> of <hi>Schiſme</hi> &amp; herefie; as Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> and Saint <hi>Cyprian</hi> more voluminouſly; The one, in his Diſputation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Nouatian;</hi> the other, againſt the <hi>Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt.</hi> And doubtleſſe, <hi>Suffering</hi> is not alwayes the way to Glory; 'Tis not <hi>Paſsion,</hi> but the <hi>Cauſe</hi> of it, that both <hi>creates,</hi> and <hi>crownes</hi> our <hi>Martyrdomes. Timeo dicere,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hieron. in <hi>cap. 5.</hi> ad Galat.</note> 
               <hi>ſed dicendum eſt; Ierome</hi> is loth to ſpeake it, but he muſt: That thoſe <hi>Corporall</hi> tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures which for Religion wee vndergoe, euen <hi>Martyrdome</hi> it ſelfe; if it be therefore vndergone, to purchaſe <hi>Admiration</hi> and <hi>Applauſe</hi> of men, <hi>fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrà ſanguis effuſus eſt,</hi> That blood was ſpilt in vaine. We honour not <hi>Martyrs,</hi> becauſe they ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, but becauſe for Chriſt, and his Church, they ſuffer. 'Tis not thy carcaſſe then, but thy <hi>Charity</hi> that caſts vp the gratefull <hi>Incenſe;</hi> and therefore thoſe that glory in their wilfull paſſions vnder a
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:135617:17"/>falſe name of <hi>Martyrdome,</hi> Heare how Saint <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> deſcants on: <hi>Ecce, venitur ad paſsionem;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. ſerm. <hi>50.</hi> de Verbis Dom.</note> 
               <hi>ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitur &amp; ad ſanguinis effuſionem; vennuur &amp; ad corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris incenſionem; &amp; támen, nihil prodeſt, quià Charitas deeſt,</hi> We offer our <hi>Bodies</hi> to the <hi>ſtake,</hi> our <hi>Blood</hi> to the <hi>flames,</hi> our <hi>Liues</hi> to the fury of the <hi>Tormentors,</hi> all this is nothing without <hi>Charity,</hi> 'tis that makes the Suffering glorious.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 13.4, 5.</note> 
               <hi>If I giue my Body to be bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Paul</hi>) and <hi>haue not Charity, it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiteth me nothing, nay had I all faith, ſo that I could re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moue mountaines, and haue not Charity, I am nothing;</hi> Not, <hi>Nullus ſum,</hi> but <hi>Nihil ſum,</hi> Not ſo much, not a <hi>Man,</hi> as not a creature, <hi>nothing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hearken then, thou ſonne of <hi>Tumult, whoſe lips enter into contention, and whoſe mouth calleth for ſtroakes; Thou</hi> which raiſeſt tempeſts in Religion,<note place="margin">Pro. 8.5.</note> and ſoweſt thy <hi>Tares</hi> of <hi>Faction</hi> amongſt the <hi>mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude;</hi> thou which bringeſt in the ſtrange <hi>Leauen</hi> of <hi>New Doctrines,</hi> and coloureſt them with thy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable allegations, whereby the Conſciences of the <hi>Simple</hi> are intangled, and the peace of the Church diſturbed, though otherwiſe perchance, thou art punctuall enough, both in thy <hi>conuerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> and thy <hi>Tenents,</hi> haſt the gifts of <hi>Prophecy,</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand'ſt all <hi>Myſtertes</hi> and all <hi>Language,</hi> yet, becauſe in ſome things thou haſt made a <hi>breach</hi> of this <hi>Harmony</hi> in the Church,<note place="margin">Schiſmatici, qui extra Eccleſians Catho icam, prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentem finunt. vilam, in ignens eunt aeternum. Aug. ſeu potius. <hi>Fulgent.</hi> de fide ad Petrum Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conum, <hi>cap. 38</hi>
               </note> thou art a <hi>Rebell</hi> both to it, and thy Chriſt; and except by <hi>Retra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation</hi> and <hi>Submiſsion</hi> thou art recald to the <hi>Fold</hi> from which thou haſt wandred, thou ſtand'ſt <hi>out-law'd</hi> and excommunicate to <hi>Heauen,</hi> and nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Impriſonment</hi> nor <hi>Death</hi> can make atonement
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:135617:18"/>for thy <hi>Miſtreadings.</hi> Is this harſh? 'Tis Saint <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtines,</hi> and he will yet goe farther: <hi>A Schiſmaticke</hi> brought vnto the <hi>take;</hi> not for that <hi>Error</hi> which did ſeparate him from the Church, but for the truth of the <hi>Word</hi> and <hi>Sacrament</hi> which he doth elſe maintaine, ſuffering the <hi>Temporall</hi> flames, to auoyde the <hi>Eternall,</hi> and beares it patiently; though that <hi>Patience</hi> be commendable, and a gift of God, yet (becauſe in part a <hi>Schiſmaticke</hi>) not of that kind of gifts which are imparted <hi>filijs Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuſalem,</hi> but to thoſe alſo which are <hi>filij concubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narum</hi> (ſaith the Father) which euen earnall <hi>Iewes,</hi> and <hi>Heretickes</hi> may haue; and concludes at length, that <hi>This</hi> ſuffering and patience no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing profits <hi>Him</hi> towards <hi>Heauen;</hi> but ſuppoſes that the great <hi>Iudgement</hi> will be in this more to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable to <hi>Him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aug.</hi> lib. <hi>de Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entia,</hi> cap. 26.27.28.</note> 
               <hi>Quàm ſi Chriſtum negando torme ta mortémque vitâſſet,</hi> Then if by denying Chriſt, he had euaded the cruelty of his Death and <hi>Torment:</hi> in his Booke <hi>de Patientia,</hi> 28. chapter.</p>
            <p>You haue heard what <hi>primitiue</hi> times haue done for the barke and out-ſide of <hi>Religton;</hi> the very skin and ſhell of <hi>Chriſtianity;</hi> Let vs now com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare them a little with our owne; and wee ſhall finde, that they haue not any-whit gone beyond vs in the <hi>Externall</hi> profeſſion of ſincerity, tho in their ſuffering and <hi>Tortures</hi> they haue much. We haue deceitfull workers as well as they,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 11.13.</note> 
               <hi>Transfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming themſelues into the Apoſtles of Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 5.20.</note> 
               <hi>which glory in appearance, and not in heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We abhorre, <hi>That Age</hi> ſhould out-doe ours, either in <hi>Hypocriſie</hi> or <hi>prophaneneſſe,</hi> wee haue our
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:135617:18"/>
               <hi>Donatiſts</hi> and <hi>Cathariſts,</hi> and <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> as plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully as they; and ſome beſides, <hi>They</hi> had not; the <hi>Browniſt,</hi> the <hi>Barrowiſt,</hi> and the <hi>Familiſt,</hi> and one more that both foſters and incloſes all theſe, (may he be whiſper'd without offence, my <hi>Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren</hi>) the <hi>Puritan;</hi> but he will not be Titled ſo; the very Name hangs in his Iawes, and the chiefe way to diſcouer him, is to call him ſo; That fires and nettles him, and ſo repining at the Name, he ownes it; and queſtionleſſe 'tis his, though he ſhrowd and vaile it vnder the word <hi>Brethren</hi> in the Text; whoſe <hi>Purity</hi> conſiſts much in waſhing of the <hi>out-ward man,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vide Ro. Art</hi> 19. <hi>A.</hi> 1. <hi>prop. vbi ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat H. N.</hi> 1. ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort c. 13. § 10. the <hi>Brewaiſts</hi> to <hi>Cartwright,</hi> page 39. <hi>Barrow</hi> in his diſcouery, p. 33.</note> whilſt their <hi>Tenents</hi> looke to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards a <hi>Legall</hi> righteouſneſſe, and a trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant and glorified condition of man here vpon earth; profeſſing by their open <hi>Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlets,</hi> that the <hi>viſible</hi> Church, the <hi>true</hi> viſible Church, is deuoid of <hi>Sinne</hi> and <hi>Sinners,</hi> and for <hi>Manners</hi> cannot <hi>erre;</hi> and therefore <hi>Paradox</hi> it, That the <hi>Aſſemblies</hi> of good and bad together, are no Church, but <hi>Heapes</hi> of prophane men; as if in one field,<note place="margin">Math. 25.</note> there were not as well <hi>Tares</hi> as <hi>Corne,</hi> in one houſe, veſſels of wood and <hi>earth, as of gold and ſiluer;</hi> a <hi>Mixture</hi> of good and bad,<note place="margin">Math. 23.</note> in all <hi>Congregations;</hi> which as an <hi>Embleme</hi> of the Church viſible, our <hi>Sauiour</hi> types-out in the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable of the <hi>Sower,</hi> the <hi>Marriage,</hi> and the <hi>Virgins;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 13.</note> Nay his <hi>Bleſſed Spouſe,</hi> of her ſelfe, freely profeſſes her deformity, <hi>Tho I am comely, I am blacke,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cant. 1.5.</note> 
               <hi>O yee Daughters of</hi> Ieruſalem, <hi>blacke as the Tents of</hi> Kedar. And yet Theſe will haue her all <hi>cleane</hi> and <hi>louely,</hi> like a face without ſpot, or wrinkle; when wee know a Mole or Wart (ſometimes) beautifies a
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:135617:19"/>feature, and in this <hi>Warre</hi> of <hi>oppoſites,</hi> there is both gracefulneſſe, and <hi>Luſtre;</hi> and therefore I ſuppoſe the Church was firſt compar'd vnto the <hi>Moone,</hi> not ſo much for <hi>change,</hi> as <hi>obnubila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> being obuious to <hi>clouds,</hi> and Eclipſes; and when 'tis at cleareſt, 'tis not without a <hi>mole</hi> in her cheeke neither, at leaſt-wife, to an <hi>ocular</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion or if it were all faire and <hi>Lueid,</hi> yet, 'tis by way of <hi>Influence,</hi> beam'd from a greater <hi>light,</hi> borrowed, not her owne; ſo is this of the Church too; one <hi>un</hi> of righteouſneſſe enlightens <hi>Both,</hi> and therefore, <hi>Woe vnto them, that call Light, Darkenes</hi> &amp; <hi>Darknes, Light;</hi> make a Church of it ſelfe ſhine, which cannot, or not ſhine, which might, if they were not, by others; dogmatically, &amp; pere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torily laying downe, that <hi>where Errors are there is no True Church</hi> (when there was neuer any, nor will be, whil'ſt 'tis <hi>militant,</hi> without them,) But <hi>They</hi> are no more of the ſubſtance of our <hi>Religion,</hi> or any <hi>Eſſentiall</hi> part of our Churches <hi>Doctrine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ro. Artie.</hi> in the Preface.</note> then ill humours which be <hi>in,</hi> are <hi>of</hi> the <hi>Body,</hi> or Dregs in a veſſell of wine, part of the wine, or veſſell.</p>
            <p>'Tis true, ſome <hi>Ceremonies</hi> we retaine yet, as matters of <hi>Indifferency,</hi> and not of <hi>Subſtance,</hi> and theſe (forſooth) are ſo hainous, that they are <hi>Thornes</hi> in their ſides, and prickles in their eyes; matter of <hi>Ceremony,</hi> is now matter of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> and rather then ſubſcribe, <hi>Silence, Suſpenſion, Impriſonment,</hi> they venture on, and ſometimes ſuffer too; where <hi>A Brethren-Contribution</hi> more fats them, then al the Fortunes they were maſters of before; and this (beloued) cannot be <hi>zeale,</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:135617:19"/>but <hi>Schiſme,</hi> or if it bee <hi>zeale,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Rom. 10.2.</note> it wants <hi>Eyes,</hi> and <hi>Intellectuals,</hi> 'tis not <hi>according to knowledge;</hi> For what <hi>Iudgement</hi> would expoſe our Body vnto priſon? our Calling to the ſtaine of <hi>Separation,</hi> and <hi>Reuolt,</hi> for a thing meerely of <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differency</hi> and <hi>Ceremony?</hi> No, there is more in it, then This; the <hi>Rochet, Tippet,</hi> and the <hi>Surpleſſe</hi> is not that they ſhoot at, but the thing call'd <hi>Parity; Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> they like not for the <hi>Ephod,</hi> and the <hi>Rod;</hi> they ſpeake <hi>power,</hi> and <hi>command,</hi> and ſo intimate <hi>obedience;</hi> But theſe ſtruggle for <hi>equa lity;</hi> the <hi>Eccleſiaſticke Hierarchy</hi> they would demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, <hi>Epiſcopall corruption</hi> is the great Eye-ſore; <hi>Downe with it, downe with it, euen to the ground.</hi> And yet I dare ſay, there are ſome ſubtle <hi>Pioners,</hi> and ſecret <hi>Mutiners</hi> in Common-wealth, pretending plauſibly to the flouriſhing of <hi>Religion,</hi> which if they could once glory in that <hi>Babel</hi> they ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to erect, they car'd not, if <hi>eruſalem</hi> were <hi>An heape of ſtones;</hi> 'Tis impoſſible, that Ciuill Authority can euer ſubſiſt without the other; and if there be once a full rent &amp; flaw in Church-policy, what can we expect from that of <hi>State,</hi> or either, but vaſt <hi>Anarchy,</hi> and <hi>Confuſion?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus, he that ſtrikes at the <hi>Myter,</hi> God grant he catch'th not at the <hi>Scepter,</hi> and (if he could graſpe it) the very <hi>Thunderbolt;</hi> no <hi>Biſhop,</hi> no <hi>King,</hi> and ſo by conſequence no God; <hi>He</hi> proclaimes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe the God of <hi>Order,</hi> and Theſe would make him the <hi>Father</hi> of <hi>Confuſion;</hi> and ſo, in circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance diſgod him too, ſeeing his greateſt glory conſiſts in the <hi>Harmony</hi> of his Creatures, the <hi>Peace</hi> of his Church, and vnanimity of his <hi>Saints</hi>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:135617:20"/>and Seruants; and therefore (brethren) let me beſeech you in the words of the <hi>Apoſtle, Marke them which cauſe Diuiſions,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 6.17, 18.</note> 
               <hi>and offences, contrary to the Doctrine which you haue heard, and auoyd them. For they that are ſuch, ſerue not our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, but their owne Belly, and by good words, and faire ſpeeches, deceiue the hearts of the ſimple, Rom.</hi> 16.17, 18, <hi>ver.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I haue yet but <hi>Beſeech't</hi> you in the words of an <hi>Apoſtle;</hi> Let me warne you alſo in the Language of a <hi>Sauiour, Beware of Thoſe which come to you in ſheeps clothing,</hi> with ſuch a Caſt of <hi>Mortification</hi> and <hi>Integrity,</hi> as if their conuerſation ſpake no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but <hi>Immaculateneſſe, when within they are rauening wolues:</hi> ſuch as will not onely <hi>tondere pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus,</hi> and <hi>deglubere;</hi> but <hi>deuorare</hi> too; ſubuert whole houſes for filthy lucre:<note place="margin">Tit. 1.13.</note> 
               <hi>You ſhall know them by their fruite;</hi> Their fruite vnto the eye beautifull and glorious, but to the finger, <hi>Duſt</hi> and <hi>Smoake;</hi> or if not by their <hi>fruite,</hi> by their <hi>Leaues,</hi> you may, a few wind-falne vertues which they piece and ſowe together to couer their owne Nakedneſſe. Will you haue them in their full <hi>Dreſſe</hi> and <hi>por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traiture?</hi> Take the draught and paterne, then from the <hi>Phariſee, Mathew</hi> 23. There the <hi>character</hi> is <hi>exact;</hi> where if you obſerue, They are twice cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Blind Guides: Blindneſſe</hi> of <hi>knowledge</hi> brings on <hi>Blindneſſe</hi> of <hi>Heart;</hi> and therefore twice alſo <hi>Fooles,</hi> and <hi>Blind; ver.</hi> 17.19. To this <hi>Blindneſſe</hi> of <hi>Heart, Pride</hi> is annex'd; <hi>They make broad their Phylacteries, and inlarge the Borders of their Garments; ver.</hi> 5. To this <hi>Pride, vaine-glory; They loue greetings in the Alarket, vppermoſt roomes at feaſts, and chiefe
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:135617:20"/>ſeates in the Synagogues; ver.</hi> 6.7. To this <hi>Vaine-glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Hypocriſie; They make cleane the out-ſide of the cup and platter, and for a pretence make long prayers; and all to be ſeene of men, v.</hi> 14.25. To this <hi>Hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, Spirituall malice; They ſhut vp the Kingdome of Heauen againſt men, for they neither goe in themſelues, nor ſuffer them that are entring, to goe in, ver.</hi> 13. Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to this <hi>Malice,</hi> there is <hi>vncharitableneſſe; They bind heauy Burdens, and grieuous to be borne, and lay them on mens ſhoulders, but they Themſelues will not moue them with one of their fingers, ver.</hi> 4. Rare per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, doubtleſſe, for the <hi>Sanctified</hi> Child of God! Obſerue the Catalogue, <hi>Blindneſſe of Heart, Pride, Vaine-glory, Hypocrifie, Malice, and Vncha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritableneſſe:</hi> Let vs make it out, <hi>Enuy,</hi> and <hi>all Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitableneſſe,</hi> and then <hi>Libera nos, Domine, Good Lord deliuer vs;</hi> deliuer vs from all falſe-hood in his Seruices, and faction againſt his Church, that we may be his <hi>Miniſters</hi> in <hi>Sincerity,</hi> and not in <hi>ſhew,</hi> as thoſe falſe <hi>Teachers</hi> were of old, or our <hi>Braine-ſicke</hi> and diſcontented <hi>Neotericks</hi> at the preſent, whom Saint <hi>Paul</hi> diſcouers by a double <hi>Attribute,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>vaniloqui, &amp; Seductores; vnruly and vaine-talkers,</hi> and <hi>Decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, Titus</hi> 1.10. They talke (it ſhould ſeeme) They doe not <hi>Teach;</hi> and talke <hi>vainely</hi> too;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>I ſtius in</hi> cap. 1. Tit. v. 10.11.</note> and not onely ſo, but this <hi>vanity</hi> muſt be nois'd, <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rulineſſe</hi> goes with it,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lectio Hieron. in</hi> 1. cap. Tit. v. 10.11.</note> and Thoſe which in their <hi>Doctrines</hi> are vaine and vntuly too, ſometimes proue <hi>Deceiuers, Mentium Decepteres,</hi> (as <hi>Ierome</hi> reades it on the Text) <hi>Deceiuers</hi> of <hi>mindes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Tim. 3.6.</note> of <hi>weake</hi> and <hi>ſimple mindes, Mechanicks,</hi> and <hi>captiu'd women,</hi> which haue beene the <hi>diſciples</hi> of
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:135617:21"/>all <hi>Schiſmes</hi> and all <hi>Hereſies</hi> in al <hi>Ages.</hi> And ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed are the chiefeſt <hi>Proficients</hi> in their Schooles now: for none are ſo pinn'd to the ſtrict obſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their <hi>Precepts,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vide</hi> 2. Tim. 4. ver 3.4.</note> as theſe <hi>Silly ones.</hi> There is nothing ſo furious as an ignorant <hi>zeale,</hi> ſo violent as a factious <hi>Holineſſe;</hi> and therefore when their <hi>Doctrines</hi> or their <hi>practices</hi> are touch'd vnto the <hi>Quicke,</hi> and made (once) the ſubiect of a Pulpit <hi>Reprchenſion;</hi> their Charity is preſently on the Racke; the <hi>Braſſe</hi> ſounds loud, and the <hi>Cymball</hi> tinckles ſhrill, their <hi>Cenſures</hi> are full-charg'd, and come on like a peale of <hi>Great ſhot,</hi> thicke and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Cymball</hi> (as <hi>Caietan</hi> obſerues) was an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument of old,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vide Eſtium in</hi> 1. Cor. 13.1.</note> 
               <hi>Magis ſonorum, quàm muſicum, not ſo muſicall as loud</hi> and of more noyſe then me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lody, and ſuch as <hi>women</hi> onely vſed, both in their times of <hi>Triumph</hi> and <hi>Deuotion.</hi> A pretty <hi>Inuention</hi> for <hi>weakeneſſe</hi> and <hi>child-hood</hi> to play withall, and be it ſpoken without diſparagement of ſome glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries in that <hi>Sexe,</hi> a fit <hi>type</hi> of <hi>women</hi> and their <hi>frailties;</hi> who, for the moſt part are taken rather with the ſound of things, then the things them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and are ſeldome without this Inſtrument of Noiſe about them. The <hi>Tongue</hi> is their proper <hi>Cymball,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 150.</note> not the <hi>well-tun'd Cymball Dauid</hi> ſpeakes of; but the <hi>Loud Cymball,</hi> with which they doe not ſo much praiſe God, as ſometimes diſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage men; Their <hi>Morality,</hi> and their <hi>zeale</hi> are neere one, a <hi>ſhrilneſſe</hi> as well in their <hi>Deuotion,</hi> as their <hi>Actrons,</hi> and their <hi>practice</hi> in both is a very <hi>Tinckling;</hi> Tinckling with their <hi>Feete,</hi> leade the <hi>Daunce</hi> to the next <hi>Conuenticle; Tinckling</hi> with the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:135617:21"/>
               <hi>tongue too;</hi> Great <hi>talkers,</hi> in <hi>Diuinity,</hi> and if they could exchange a <hi>Parlour</hi> for a <hi>Church,</hi> or a <hi>ſtoole</hi> for a <hi>Pulpit,</hi> they would <hi>preach too,</hi> &amp; ('tis thought) <hi>Edifie</hi> as much as their <hi>zealous Paſtor.</hi> But <hi>Away</hi> with thoſe <hi>Ecchoes</hi> in <hi>Religion,</hi> fitter for <hi>Silence,</hi> then <hi>Reproofe;</hi> and for <hi>pitty,</hi> then <hi>confutation;</hi> and therefore (once more) <hi>I Beſeech</hi> you, and with the phraſe of an <hi>Apoſtle too,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> vltims.</note> 
               <hi>Bee not carried about with diuers and ſtrange Doctrines,</hi> Halt and limp not betweene <hi>Innouation</hi> and an eſtabliſh'd <hi>Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline.</hi> But (as <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid to the <hi>Cripple</hi>) <hi>In the Name of Ieſus Chriſt of</hi> Nazareth, <hi>riſe vp and walke;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 3.6.</note> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne vnto the Church, whence ye are ſtraggling; not <hi>to your Stepdame,</hi> but <hi>your mother,</hi> the <hi>Mother</hi> of whom you were borne and nurs'd; dry thoſe teares ſhe ſheads for you; <hi>peace</hi> thoſe ſighs, and groanes, &amp; complaints, which ſhe wailes for you; Fall vpon thoſe <hi>Armes</hi> which will embrace you, thoſe <hi>Bowels</hi> which yearne for you, thoſe <hi>Paps</hi> which gaue you ſucke. <hi>What went you to ſee? A Reed ſhake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with the wind?</hi> Yes, a very <hi>Reed,</hi> ſhake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry wind of <hi>Doctrine; A Reed</hi> with a bruized <hi>ſtalke</hi> or broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Eare,</hi> no Corne in it; or if it haue, 'tis blaſted with <hi>Sedition,</hi> fitter for the <hi>Dunghil,</hi> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the <hi>Granary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Away then from <hi>Lebanon</hi> (my Beloued) from <hi>Lebanon;</hi> Looke from the <hi>Den</hi> of <hi>Lyons,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cant. 4.8.</note> and <hi>Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines of the Leopards</hi> (where the peace of <hi>Religion</hi> is blood-ſuck't and deuour'd) and <hi>come hither to the mountaines of Myrrh; and hills of Frankincenſe; The Altars of the liuing God,</hi> where the <hi>Incenſe</hi> of his Church flames cheerefully, with no leſſe truth of <hi>deuotion,</hi> then vnanimity. <hi>Loe,</hi> her <hi>golden vials, full of odours, Sacrifices</hi> both <hi>deuout</hi> and <hi>peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able,</hi>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:135617:22"/>Such as the heart of his <hi>people</hi> offer, and not the hands, onely; <hi>Calues</hi> of our <hi>lips,</hi> and groanes of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> which touch both the <hi>cares</hi> and <hi>noſtrils</hi> of the <hi>Almighty. Let</hi> the <hi>voyce</hi> of <hi>diuiſion,</hi> then, jarre no more amongſt you, which if there were no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe to noiſe our frailties, were enough to ſpeake bondage to the <hi>fleſh,</hi> and not yet, our free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to the <hi>Spirit.</hi> For whence are <hi>ſtrifes and enury<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings? are they not from your luſts?</hi> And whilſt <hi>one ſaith, I am of Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 3.4.</note> 
               <hi>another, am of Apollo,</hi> are ye not <hi>car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall? Chriſt is not deuided,</hi> his Church is one; <hi>My Doue,<note place="margin">Cant. 6.7.</note> my vndefiled is but one, ſhe is the onely one of her mother,</hi> the <hi>choice one of her that bare Her, Can.</hi> 6.7.</p>
            <p>The Church, (you heare) is Gods <hi>onely one,</hi> his <hi>choice one; He</hi> hath no more, and <hi>we,</hi> tho many, are but <hi>one</hi> neither,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.17.</note> the <hi>Churches one, Her choiceſt one, one Body,</hi> nay, <hi>one Bread,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.17. Moreouer, <hi>Chriſts Spirit</hi> is but <hi>one;</hi> tho it bee in many, 'tis there ſtill one <hi>Spirit,</hi> no <hi>diuiſion</hi> where that is, but all <hi>peace;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.3.</note> and therefore 'tis call'd the <hi>vnity of the Spirit;</hi> and this <hi>vnity</hi> muſt be ſtill kept in <hi>the bond of peace.</hi> Marke, here's no wanering, or <hi>Temporary peace;</hi> but this <hi>peace</hi> muſt be ſtill kept, and not <hi>ſtightly</hi> kept, but there is a <hi>Tye</hi> on the keeping of it, <hi>The Bond of peace:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.3.</note> and 'tis this <hi>Bond</hi> that makes the <hi>vnity,</hi> and this <hi>vnity</hi> that keepes the <hi>peace,</hi> and this <hi>peace</hi> that preſerues the <hi>Spirit,</hi> ſo that 'tis ſtill an <hi>vnity of Spirit,</hi> kept in the <hi>Bond</hi> of <hi>peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Come hither, then, my Faithfull <hi>Brother in the Lord,</hi> and let vs no more <hi>cenſure,</hi> but <hi>expoſtulate.</hi> Haſt <hi>Thou</hi> the <hi>true Faith</hi> thou ſo much glorieſt in? where is thy <hi>zeale?</hi> haſt thou true <hi>zeale?</hi> where is thy <hi>Charity?</hi> haſt thou true <hi>Charity?</hi> why art thou
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:135617:22"/>
               <hi>Tumultuous?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn. 13.35.</note> 
               <hi>By this ſhall you know</hi> (ſaith <hi>Chriſt</hi>) that <hi>you are my Diſciples, if you loue one another. Mutuall</hi> agreement begets <hi>Loue,</hi> and this <hi>Loue</hi> makes the <hi>Diſciple,</hi> and this <hi>Diſciple</hi> is <hi>knowne to be Chriſts,</hi> by a <hi>Si diligeretis, onely, if yee loue one another.</hi> And therefore in the firſt <hi>Dawne</hi> and <hi>riſing</hi> of the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Church,</hi> the <hi>chiefe</hi> thing remark'd in it by the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> was the <hi>Chriſtian Loue:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tertul. Apol. <hi>36.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Vide vt inuicemſe diligunt! vt pro alterutro mori ſint parati!</hi> as <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſtories it. Lo how they <hi>Loue!</hi> the <hi>Heathens</hi> cry, How ready to <hi>Dye</hi> one for another! But this <hi>Loue</hi> of the <hi>Brother</hi> vnto <hi>Death,</hi> I preſſe not here; (for the very <hi>Infidels</hi> had their <hi>Commorientes,</hi> as well as <hi>we</hi>) but <hi>Loue</hi> vnto <hi>Sincerity</hi> and <hi>Conſtancy,</hi> of which he that is deſtitute, falls <hi>ſhort</hi> both in <hi>Religion,</hi> and <hi>Morality.</hi> And therefore that <hi>Text</hi> in Saint <hi>Peter</hi> runs <hi>Methodically, Feare God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.17.</note> 
               <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour the King,</hi> but firſt, <hi>Loue the Brotherhood;</hi> as if there could be no true feare of God, or honour of the King, except there be firſt <hi>Loue</hi> to thy <hi>Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;</hi> to thy <hi>Brother?</hi> nay, the <hi>Brother-hood:</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſaith the Greeke, <hi>Achava,</hi> the Hebrew;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Beza Annot. in</hi> 1. Pet. 2 10.</note> 
               <hi>Brotherhood,</hi> for the company and coniunction of <hi>Brethren</hi> in the Church; and in <hi>this,</hi> not ſo much a Coniunction of <hi>perſons,</hi> as of <hi>Mindes,</hi> other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe 'tis no Church. And therefore the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of them that beleeued at the <hi>Apoſtles Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> were ſaid to bee of <hi>one Soule, and one heart, Acts</hi> 4.32. And this <hi>one Soule, and one heart;</hi> S. <hi>Paul</hi> calls <hi>one minde, and one Iudgement:</hi> And this <hi>one minde</hi> and <hi>one Iudgement,</hi> muſt not be thinly mixt,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.10.12.</note> but <hi>perfectly ioyn'd together,</hi> and ſo <hi>ioyn'd together,</hi> that there be no <hi>Diuiſion among vs;</hi> and therefore
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:135617:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>he coniures his <hi>Corinthians</hi> by the <hi>Name of Ieſus Chriſt;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 15.5, 6.</note> not onely to <hi>Doe,</hi> but to <hi>Speake</hi> the ſame thing. <hi>I Beſeech you Brethren, by the Name of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, that ye all ſpeake the ſame thing, that there be no Diuiſion amongst you, but that ye be perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctly ioyn'd together, in one minde, and the ſame Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.10.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Maximum indicium malae mentis fluctuatio,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sen. Epiſt. <hi>121.</hi>
               </note> Ree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling betweene <hi>opinion and opinion;</hi> is a <hi>Mentall drunkenneſſe</hi> and there is no ſuch <hi>Index</hi> of a <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praued</hi> Diſpoſition, as <hi>wauing</hi> &amp; <hi>vnſettledneſſe.</hi> And therefore the <hi>Stoicke</hi> deſcribing the <hi>vnconſtant</hi> man,<note place="margin">Senec. Jbid.</note> 
               <hi>Thus</hi> laſhes him, <hi>Nunquàm eundem nec ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem quidem, ſed in diuerſum aberrat;</hi> He ſo trauer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and wanders in himſelfe, that hee is neither the ſame, nor like, but diuerſe. So that the <hi>Wiſe</hi> man is the <hi>Man</hi> onely of <hi>Reſolution,</hi> for <hi>He</hi> is <hi>one,</hi> and the <hi>ſame ſtill: Praeter Sapientem nemo vnus, Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neca</hi> tells his <hi>Ducillius</hi> in his 126. Epiſtle. And doubtleſſe, 'tis this <hi>one minde</hi> and <hi>one Iudgement,</hi> that makes both the diſcreet <hi>Moraliſt</hi> and the wiſe <hi>Chriſtian: Videmus qualis ſit, quantus ſit,</hi> and <hi>vnus ſit:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epiſt. 26.</note> the ſame <hi>Seneca. Vnanimity</hi> is the <hi>Soule</hi> of <hi>Brother-hood,</hi> whether in that of <hi>Nature,</hi> or of <hi>Grace;</hi> And therefore, what <hi>Abraham,</hi> of old, ſaid vnto <hi>Lot,</hi> is worthy both of your memory and obſeruation,<note place="margin">Geneſ. 13.8.</note> 
               <hi>Let there be no ſtrife betweene me and thee, nor betweene my Heardſmen, and thy Heardſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men; why? We are Brethren</hi> as if the very word did inuolue <hi>vnion,</hi> and where there was <hi>Brother-hood,</hi> there could be no <hi>ſtrife;</hi> no not amongſt their very <hi>Heardſmen,</hi> that brawling <hi>Regiment,</hi> which, for the moſt part, are as vnruly as the Droues they
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:135617:23"/>keepe; and in ſome things 'tis diſputable, which is the verier <hi>Beaſt;</hi> for they both goe one way, <hi>non quá eundum eſt, ſed quâ itur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sen. Epiſt. <hi>135.</hi>
               </note> As the multitude treads, ſo they follow, ſquadron'd into a <hi>Faction,</hi> as <hi>That</hi> is, not onely in the <hi>State,</hi> but the Church too; And ſo 'twas of <hi>old,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 14.4.</note> in the time of the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles,</hi> when at <hi>Iconmum</hi> there was a great <hi>vprore</hi> amongſt the <hi>Iewes</hi> and <hi>Gentiles,</hi> about the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas;</hi> in ſtead of ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing the fury of the <hi>Tumult,</hi> the <hi>Rabble</hi> of the City was <hi>Diuided;</hi> and part held with the <hi>Iewes,</hi> and part with the <hi>Apoſtles, Act.</hi> 14.4.</p>
            <p>Thus <hi>popular conuocations</hi> were euer the <hi>Nurſes</hi> of <hi>Diſtraction;</hi> and <hi>Theſe,</hi> now occaſion the <hi>Hubub</hi> and <hi>Out-cries</hi> in <hi>Our Church,</hi> the ſtrife is not ſo much betweene <hi>Loo,</hi> and <hi>Abraham,</hi> as their <hi>Heardſmen,</hi> the <hi>People</hi> more ſide it in <hi>Religion,</hi> then their <hi>Paſtors</hi> doe; and that's the beſt <hi>Doctrine</hi> which <hi>They</hi> fancy; not what the <hi>Others</hi> teach. And to this purpoſe, <hi>They</hi> haue gotten, lately into moſt <hi>Corpor ations</hi> of the <hi>Kingdome,</hi> certaine <hi>Lapwing-Dinines,</hi> and featherleſſe Profeſſors of their owne Cut; preſcribe them <hi>Principles</hi> which they may not tran ſgreſſe; and not onely their <hi>Poſture, Habit,</hi> and <hi>Conuerſation,</hi> but the very <hi>Methode, Tone</hi> and <hi>Language</hi> cued them. Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable <hi>Age,</hi> when <hi>Diuinity</hi> ſhall be thus ſlau'd to a <hi>Stipend</hi> and <hi>a Trencher!</hi> and the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> for a <hi>morſell of bread!</hi> or ſome <hi>Mechanicke,</hi> or <hi>Leane-cheek'd</hi> Contribution, ſhall diſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage the <hi>Powre</hi> and <hi>Sacredneſſe</hi> of their <hi>Keyes!</hi> But fie on this <hi>Factious Holineſſe,</hi> this <hi>Iezebel</hi> in <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,</hi> that ſmells too much of the <hi>Painter,</hi> and
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:135617:24"/>his <hi>Varniſh:</hi> Let it no more with <hi>vncharitable</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions, or <hi>nouelty</hi> of <hi>Doctrine,</hi> or <hi>vnſeaſonable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> of <hi>ſuggeſtion,</hi> diſturbe the <hi>peace</hi> of our <hi>Spirituall Mother;</hi> but let her ſleepe and reſt ſweetly in that <hi>Diuine truth,</hi> which <hi>ſhe</hi> hath receiued from <hi>Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue plantations,</hi> and ſeal'd fince, with the <hi>Blood</hi> of ſo many <hi>Martyns. I charge you, O Daughters of</hi> Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, <hi>by the Roes and Hinds of the field, that ye ſtirre not, or awake my Loue, vntill ſhe pleaſe, Cant.</hi> 3.5.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>'Twas long ſince the complaint of a diſconſolate Church, and ours hath in part reuiu'd it: Ecce pace ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritudo mea amariſsima, pax ab haereticis, pax à paga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, bellum à filijs:</hi> O my bitter bitterneſſe in the dayes of peace, peace amongſt pagans, peace amongſt Heretickes, but warres and ſtruglings by the twinnes of my owne womb! My ſonnes, my diuided ſonnes, are more vnnaturall then all theſe. The Proteſtant, that hath beene ſo long the Starre of the Reformed Church, the Enſigne and Standard-bearer of true Religion, muſt be now buffeted and ſpit vpon by the obloquy and ſcorne of vp ſtart Sectaries!</p>
            <p>
               <hi>You</hi> then, that thus dig out the <hi>Bowels</hi> of your hallowed <hi>mother,</hi> and ſticke your Daggers at her very heart;<note place="margin">Serm. <hi>57.</hi> de Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerfis in Append.</note> 
               <hi>Hearke,</hi> Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> the deuout Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> All thoſe gifts and rewards of <hi>Beatitude,</hi> which God hath treaſur'd vp for his <hi>Children</hi> and <hi>Elect, in pacis conſeruatione promiſit,</hi> are appropriate onely to the <hi>Sonnes</hi> of <hi>peace.</hi> And hence is our <hi>Sauiours Beatipacifici, Bleſſed are the peace-makers;</hi> why? <hi>They ſhall be called the ſonnes of God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. Serm. <hi>463.</hi> de Temp.</note> 
               <hi>Non peruenitur ad voc abulum Filij, niſi per nomen pacifici,</hi> ſaies the <hi>Father.</hi> They had neuer beene
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:135617:24"/>called the Sonnes of God, had they not beene firſt the ſonnes of <hi>peace;</hi> nor entituled to the <hi>Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute</hi> of <hi>Bleſſed,</hi> had they not beene formerly the Sonnes of God. And therefore 'tis the <hi>Subſtance</hi> of <hi>Chriſts valediction</hi> to his Diſciples;<note place="margin">Iohn 14.27. <hi>Aug. Serm.</hi> 463. <hi>de Temp.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>My peace I leaue with you, my peace I giue vnto you: Proficiſcens voluit dare, quod deſiderabat rediens in omnibus inueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re;</hi> the ſame Saint <hi>Auguſtine;</hi> Hee gaue to all, at his departure, what he deſir'd to find in all, at his returne; his <hi>peace,</hi> his bleſſed <hi>peace:</hi> For where there is a Congregation of <hi>men,</hi> and not of <hi>opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions,</hi> or of <hi>opinions,</hi> and not of <hi>loue; Chriſt</hi> is not there with his <hi>Pax vobis:</hi> ſo that where peace is not, there is no <hi>Chriſt;</hi> and where no <hi>Chriſt,</hi> no <hi>Church.</hi> Thy <hi>Religion,</hi> thy <hi>Faith,</hi> thy <hi>Hope,</hi> are <hi>dead</hi> without it, thy <hi>Groanes,</hi> thy <hi>Sighs,</hi> thy <hi>Deuotions,</hi> are <hi>falſe</hi> and <hi>empty,</hi> like <hi>vaults</hi> that ſound meerely from their hollowneſſe; thy ſelfe like an Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that's crack'd, or a ſtring that jarr's. And therefore to the <hi>peace-leſſe Brother,</hi> that of <hi>Tertul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> to the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> ſhall be both my <hi>Aduice,</hi> and my <hi>Concluſion; Fratres veſtriſumus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tertul. Apol. <hi>36.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>iure noſtrae Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tris vnius; et ſi vos parum homines, qui mali fratres; at quanto dignius, fratres &amp; dicuntur, &amp; habentur, qui vnu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Patrem Deum agnouerunt, qui vnum Spiritum biberunt ſanctitatis, qui de vno vtero ignorantiae eiuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem, ad vnam Lucem expauerint veritatis? Itaque, quia Animâ, animóque miſcemur, nihil de rei communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catione dubitemus:</hi> Since we haue <hi>one God,</hi> our <hi>Father; one Chriſt,</hi> our <hi>Brother; one Church,</hi> our <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; one Spirit,</hi> our <hi>Comforter;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 4. <hi>vli.</hi>
               </note> let vs all haue <hi>one minde, one heart, one peace,</hi> our <hi>Director;</hi> that ſo the <hi>God</hi> of <hi>peace,</hi> which is aboue <hi>All,</hi> may be through
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:135617:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>All,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cant. 4.15.</note> and in vs <hi>All.</hi> And then <hi>Ariſe, O North</hi> and <hi>come, O South, and blow on my Garden, that the ſpices thereof may flow out.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cant. 7.12.</note> Ariſe yee <hi>Soueraigne winds</hi> of the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and breath on this garden of the <hi>Spouſe, where the Pomegranates bud forth, and the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der grapes appeare,</hi> that the <hi>fragrant odours</hi> of theſe her <hi>Plants</hi> may bee both increas'd and diſpes'd, and at length carryed into the <hi>Noſtirls</hi> of her <hi>well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beloued,</hi> who ſhall bring her out of this <hi>Wilderneſſe</hi> below,<note place="margin">Cant. 3.6.</note> like <hi>pillers of ſmoke, perfum'd with Myrrhe and Incenſe,</hi> which as <hi>ſweete ſauours,</hi> ſhall aſcend on high, where the <hi>Day</hi> breakes, and <hi>ſhadowes</hi> flye away, where <hi>Darkeneſſe</hi> is baniſh'd euerlaſtingly, and the <hi>Sunne</hi> of <hi>Righteouſneſſe</hi> ſhines for euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more. To <hi>whom,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <closer>Gloria in excelſis Deo.</closer>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <hi>Haec, atque huiuſmodi verba obtrectantium, ſiuè non obtrectando, ſed quaerendo talia loquentium, ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſius fortaſsè refellerem, niſi hae diſceptationes habe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentur cum viris liber aliter inſtitutis:</hi> 
                  <bibl>Aug. <hi>de Apoll. &amp;</hi> Apul. <hi>ad</hi> Marcellinum. <hi>Epist.</hi> 5. <hi>Reſpon.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
